<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proverbs English, French, Dutch, Italian, and Spanish. All Englished and alphabetically digested. By N.R. Gent.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R56</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1935_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203333</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115502</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115502)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 240:E1935[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proverbs English, French, Dutch, Italian, and Spanish. All Englished and alphabetically digested. By N.R. Gent.</title>
                  <author>N. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 151, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Simon Miller at the Star in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With three final advertisement leaves and an additional leaf with "A book of proverbs" printed vertically.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Proverbs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PROVERBS
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>French,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dutch,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Italian,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and <hi>Spaniſh.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
All Engliſhed and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabetically Digeſted.</p>
            <p>By <hi>N. R.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Simon Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dar</hi> at the Star in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Judicious READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving long ſince, upon the Advice of my Friends, begun a Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> which I had finiſhed, had I not fell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto that misfortune that
<pb facs="tcp:115502:3"/>doth commonly attend upon the greateſt Reſolutions; I mean, I could not perfect what I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, by reaſon of ſome occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that did interpoſe: Wherefore I was conſtrained to lay it aſide till a more favourable aſpect would countenance my endeavours. Now having an opportunity, I have Publiſhed that which the greateſt Students of our time did never ſet upon.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you how
<pb facs="tcp:115502:3"/>uſefull thoſe Sentences are for your Knowledge, that there is nothing more Elegant or Eloquent, then to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix in your ſerious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, theſe <hi>Proverbs,</hi> to illuſtrate your ſtile in writing; and this is the greateſt uſe. There happens many times, that a man cannot find Expreſſions rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily for a Noble Intention, but in a way that is either too common for the manner,
<pb facs="tcp:115502:4"/>or too mean for the matter; now in ſuch a pinch, to clap in an honeſt <hi>Proverb,</hi> the aptneſſe of the phraſe, and feſtivity of the Joke, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes ſatisfaction to the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and pleaſure to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Now here you have, with much labour, Collected almoſt all the <hi>Proverbs</hi> ſpoken, whether in <hi>Engliſh, French, Dutch, Italian,</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> and all ſutable to the capacity of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb facs="tcp:115502:4"/>and ſo methodically in Alphabet diſpoſed, that at the firſt ſight almoſt, a man may furniſh himſelf according to his Occaſion. Thus wiſhing you the ſame content in the Reading that I had in the writing, I remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend <hi>N. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>REader, be pleaſed to take notice,
<pb facs="tcp:115502:5"/>that there is now in the Preſſe, and will be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent about <hi>Michalmas</hi> Term, in <hi>folio,</hi> Eighteen Books of rare <hi>Secrets,</hi> Collected out of the choiceſt Authors, both Antient and Modern; firſt deſigned by <hi>John VVecker</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Phyſick, augmented and much enlarged by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>R. Read.</hi> The like never before in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115502:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROVERBS</hi> Engliſh, French, Italian, Spaniſh, Dutch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="A" type="proverb">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Fools bolt is ſoon ſhot. —</item>
                  <item>As good loſt as found.</item>
                  <item>A Candle lights others, and conſumes it ſelf.</item>
                  <item>An ill wound may be cured, not an ill Name.</item>
                  <item>A barren Woman can never be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</item>
                  <item>A Poet in adverſity can hardly make Verſes.</item>
                  <item>A huge Building, a low Foundation.</item>
                  <item>All who come into a Church, ſay not their Prayers.</item>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115502:6"/>
                  <item>A Fool and wealth, cannot poſſeſſe each other.</item>
                  <item>A clear bargain, a dear Friend.</item>
                  <item>Affections are the wings of the ſoul.</item>
                  <item>A good Winter brings a good Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</item>
                  <item>A Cat may look on a King.</item>
                  <item>A fool may ſometimes give a wiſe man counſell.</item>
                  <item>An unhappy Boy makes a good man.</item>
                  <item>A carrion Kite will never be a good Hauk.</item>
                  <item>A bow long bent, at laſt waxeth weak.</item>
                  <item>A cloſe mouth catcheth no flies.</item>
                  <item>A good beginning, a good ending.</item>
                  <item>A hungery belly hath no ears.</item>
                  <item>At length the Fox turns Monk.</item>
                  <item>A Cur will bite, before he bark.</item>
                  <item>As lecherous as a cock-ſparrow.</item>
                  <item>A dog hath a day.</item>
                  <item>Agree, for the Law is coſtly.</item>
                  <item>A Friend will help at a dead lift.</item>
                  <item>A Place, or Office diſcovers a man, what he is.</item>
                  <item>As tender as a Prieſts Lemmon.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115502:6"/>
                  <item>A broken ſleeve, holdeth the arm back.</item>
                  <item>A full Purſe, and a fat Bribe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand contention.</item>
                  <item>An old Drunkard is hardly reclaimed.</item>
                  <item>A fool and his money is ſoon parted.</item>
                  <item>After meat muſtard.</item>
                  <item>At Court every one for himſelf.</item>
                  <item>A Friend is not ſo ſoon gotten, as loſt.</item>
                  <item>An idle man ſeldom virtuous.</item>
                  <item>After black cloudes, clear weather.</item>
                  <item>A Houſe and a Woman ſuit excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently.</item>
                  <item>A coole mouth and warm feet live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</item>
                  <item>A fool may throw a ſtone in a Well, which a hundred wiſe men cannot get out.</item>
                  <item>A Friend in Court is worth a penny in Purſe.</item>
                  <item>After a ſtorm comes a calm.</item>
                  <item>A heart content hath the world at command.</item>
                  <item>A Phyſician hath three faces.</item>
                  <item>A Friend is never known, till a man hath need.</item>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115502:7"/>
                  <item>All covet, all looſe.</item>
                  <item>A diligent Scholar, and the Maſters paid.</item>
                  <item>A good man can no more harm, then a Sheep.</item>
                  <item>A Ship and a Woman are ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing.</item>
                  <item>As fit as a Pudding for a Fryars mouth.</item>
                  <item>A calm pretends a ſtorm.</item>
                  <item>A living Dog is better then a dead Lyon.</item>
                  <item>A good tale ill told, in the telling is mar'd.</item>
                  <item>A vapourer in words, but not in deeds.</item>
                  <item>A low hedge is eaſily leapt over.</item>
                  <item>A ſhort Grace, and a long Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</item>
                  <item>A good Jack maketh a good Gill.</item>
                  <item>A gentle heart is tyed with an eaſie thread.</item>
                  <item>After Dinner ſit a while, after Supper walk a mile.</item>
                  <item>A ſcold, a whore, and a ſlut, makes a mans life uncomfortable.</item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115502:7"/>
                  <item>A good Neighbour, a good-morrow.</item>
                  <item>An ill Bird layes a naughty Egge.</item>
                  <item>An idle head is a box for the wind.</item>
                  <item>A grunting Horſe, and a groaning Wife, never fail their Maſters.</item>
                  <item>A Friend in a corner, is better then money in a mans Purſe.</item>
                  <item>A wonder laſteth but nine daies.</item>
                  <item>A man is praiſed by his Land.</item>
                  <item>Almes never makes poor.</item>
                  <item>Age and Wedlock, tames man and Beaſt.</item>
                  <item>A good Name is ſufficient Wealth.</item>
                  <item>A ſwine over-fat is cauſe of his own bane.</item>
                  <item>As good ſleep together, as do nothing.</item>
                  <item>All is well, that ends well.</item>
                  <item>A ragged Colt may make a good Horſe.</item>
                  <item>All the proof a Pudding is in the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                  <item>As good ſit ſtill, as riſe up and fall.</item>
                  <item>A man knowes not the worth of a thing, till he wants it.</item>
                  <item>As good ſit ſtill, as be idle.</item>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115502:8"/>
                  <item>An ill weed grows apace.</item>
                  <item>A bad man hath ever bad conditions.</item>
                  <item>A ſleeping man is no better then a dead man.</item>
                  <item>A good Poet, an evil Perſon.</item>
                  <item>As ſoon goes the young Lambs skin to the Market, as the old one.</item>
                  <item>An Ox is bound by his hornes, a man by his word.</item>
                  <item>A Rat may very ill plead Law.</item>
                  <item>A ſweet tree yeeldeth ſavoury fruit.</item>
                  <item>An old Cat laps as much, as a young Kitlin.</item>
                  <item>A Gueſt and a fiſh at three daies end, grow muſty.</item>
                  <item>A bad Judge hath bad conditions.</item>
                  <item>A white wall, is a fools paper.</item>
                  <item>An old man, unfit for a young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</item>
                  <item>A dull Servant was never good for his Maſter, nor himſelf.</item>
                  <item>A Mouſe, in time, may bite in two a Cable.</item>
                  <item>As I brew, ſo muſt I needs drink.</item>
                  <item>An interprizing fool, needs little wit.</item>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115502:8"/>
                  <item>A piece of a Kid is worth two of a Cat.</item>
                  <item>At a round Table there is no diſpute of place.</item>
                  <item>A learned Wife ſeldome proves good.</item>
                  <item>Ask my companion, whether I am a Thief.</item>
                  <item>A man may bring a Horſe to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but he cannot make him drink without he will.</item>
                  <item>A hard beginning hath a good ending.</item>
                  <item>A young Saint, an old Devil.</item>
                  <item>As good to play for nought, as work for nought.</item>
                  <item>A gadding Hen, and a Houſewife, are ſoon loſt.</item>
                  <item>All that the Clerk gets, his punck de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voures.</item>
                  <item>A penny-worth of eaſe is worth two in a mans Purſe.</item>
                  <item>A man of ſtraw, is worth a woman of gold.</item>
                  <item>A ſon of a whore never did well.</item>
                  <item>A hard fought Field, where no man ſcapeth unkil'd.</item>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115502:9"/>
                  <item>A deſperate debt takes any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
                  <item>A words enough to the wiſe.</item>
                  <item>As deep drinketh the Gooſſe, as the Gander.</item>
                  <item>A poor dog, that is not worth the whiſtling.</item>
                  <item>A haſty man never wants woe.</item>
                  <item>A honey tongue, a heart of gall.</item>
                  <item>A man far from his good is nigh his harm.</item>
                  <item>All is not gold, that gliſters.</item>
                  <item>As proud comes behind, as before.</item>
                  <item>A little pot is ſoon hot.</item>
                  <item>A pound of care will not pay an ounce of debt.</item>
                  <item>A proud horſe, that will not bear his own provinder.</item>
                  <item>A ſcald head is ſoon broken.</item>
                  <item>A leg of a Lark, is worth the body of a Kite.</item>
                  <item>As long liveth a merry man, as a ſad.</item>
                  <item>A long Harveſt, of a little Corn.</item>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115502:9"/>
                  <item>A ſhrew profitable may ſerve a man reaſonable.</item>
                  <item>All is well with him, that is beloved of his neighbours.</item>
                  <item>A full belly neither fights nor flyes well.</item>
                  <item>A falſe knave needs no broker.</item>
                  <item>An unhappy boy makes a good man.</item>
                  <item>A ſhort Horſe is ſoon curried.</item>
                  <item>As the old Cock croweth ſo the young followeth.</item>
                  <item>A ſcald horſe is good enough for a ſcabd Squire.</item>
                  <item>A man is not ſo ſoon heal'd as hurt.</item>
                  <item>A man may buy gold to dear.</item>
                  <item>A curſt dog muſt be tied ſhort.</item>
                  <item>A right fool forgets himſelf.</item>
                  <item>All ſhall be well when Jack ſhall have a Gill.</item>
                  <item>An inch breaketh no Squares.</item>
                  <item>As the bell tinks, the fool thinks.</item>
                  <item>As cold as charity.</item>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115502:10"/>
                  <item>An unbidden gueſt knows not where to ſit.</item>
                  <item>All is fiſh, that come to net.</item>
                  <item>All fools are ſots, but all ſots are not fools.</item>
                  <item>A fool begins ſtrife, a wiſe man ends buſineſſe.</item>
                  <item>A bungler ſeldome fits himſelf with good tools.</item>
                  <item>A good pay-maſter ſtarts not at aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</item>
                  <item>An ill Cook, that cannot lick his own finger.</item>
                  <item>A fool oft finds himſelf ſhort of his reckoning.</item>
                  <item>An inch in a miſs, is as good as an ell.</item>
                  <item>As a man is friended, ſo the Law is ended.</item>
                  <item>An old Dog biteth ſore.</item>
                  <item>A heavy Purſe makes a light heart.</item>
                  <item>A man may hold his peace in an ill time.</item>
                  <item>A babler wearieth all the company.</item>
                  <item>An idle Husband, and empty walls, makes a light Houſewife.</item>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115502:10"/>
                  <item>A maid that giveth, yeeldeth.</item>
                  <item>A hook well loſt to get a Salmon.</item>
                  <item>A hot Winter makes a full Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</item>
                  <item>A Bird in hand is worth two in the buſh.</item>
                  <item>An honeſt woman is much worth.</item>
                  <item>A fool brooks any diſgrace.</item>
                  <item>A falſe tongue can hardly ſpeak truth.</item>
                  <item>An evening red, and a morning gray, are hopefull ſignes of a fair day.</item>
                  <item>A word hurts more then a wound.</item>
                  <item>A fly hath a ſpleen.</item>
                  <item>A woman that hath loſt her ſhame, hath loſt her reſpect, and her good Name.</item>
                  <item>A handfull of good life, is better then a buſhell of learning.</item>
                  <item>All came from, and will go to others.</item>
                  <item>A Lyons skin is never cheap.</item>
                  <item>A crooked lye, makes a ſtraight fy.</item>
                  <item>A Merchant that gaineth not, looſeth.</item>
                  <item>A bad Dog never ſees the Wolf.</item>
                  <item>An old ſack asketh much patching.</item>
                  <item>A woman and a glaſſe are ever in danger.</item>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115502:11"/>
                  <item>A woman conceales what ſhe knows not.</item>
                  <item>As good be merry as ſad.</item>
                  <item>A long tongue is a ſign of a ſhort hand.</item>
                  <item>All truths are not to be told.</item>
                  <item>A pure beauty finds more Lovers then Husbands.</item>
                  <item>A houſe pul'd down is half built up.</item>
                  <item>An after wit is every bodies wit.</item>
                  <item>A virtuous Wife is worth a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</item>
                  <item>As blind as a mole.</item>
                  <item>An ill Wife that grows not worſe, is not of the Wives the worſt.</item>
                  <item>Anger and hearts eaſe are utter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</item>
                  <item>A man muſt fiſh with a ſilver hook.</item>
                  <item>A good ſtomack is the beſt ſauce.</item>
                  <item>A ſecret is too little for one, enough for two, too much for three.</item>
                  <item>A gentle houſewife marres the Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</item>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115502:11"/>
                  <item>A broken ſack will hold no corn.</item>
                  <item>A faithfull friend what good may he do us?</item>
                  <item>A traveller may lye by authority.</item>
                  <item>A man will not looſe a Hog for a half penny worth of a tarre.</item>
                  <item>A man muſt creep before he go.</item>
                  <item>All Joy hath ſad effects in a troubled heart.</item>
                  <item>A muſled Cat was never good mouſer.</item>
                  <item>A man will be a man though he have but a hoſe on his head.</item>
                  <item>A good Winter brings a good Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</item>
                  <item>A bribe entereth every where without knocking.</item>
                  <item>A dwarf on a Giants ſhoulders ſees further of the two.</item>
                  <item>An Aſſe, though ſlow, if provok't, will kick.</item>
                  <item>A Wolf caſts his hair, but not his malice.</item>
                  <item>A frog cannot out of her bog.</item>
                  <item>A tongue hath no bone in it, yet it breaks ones back.</item>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115502:12"/>
                  <item>As welcome as water into a Ship.</item>
                  <item>A fair Wife, and a fronteir Caſtle, breed quarrels.</item>
                  <item>All Carriers are not Knaves, ſome have ſouls to be ſaved.</item>
                  <item>A fair death honours the life.</item>
                  <item>A knife that cuts not, and a friend that is worth nought, value not.</item>
                  <item>A light burden carried far, proves heavy.</item>
                  <item>As fit as a ſaddle for a Sow.</item>
                  <item>A thing done by force is not worth a ruſh.</item>
                  <item>A good bargain is a pick-purſe.</item>
                  <item>Autumnall agues are long or mortall.</item>
                  <item>A wicked mans gift hath a touch of his Maſter.</item>
                  <item>Ambition looſeth many a man.</item>
                  <item>An honeſt heart cannot diſſemble.</item>
                  <item>A cheerfull look makes a diſh a Feaſt.</item>
                  <item>All manner of vices are in a Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</item>
                  <item>A good meale, a bad meale, and a midling meale, preſerves a man in health.</item>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115502:12"/>
                  <item>A proud mind, and a beggers purſe, goes together.</item>
                  <item>A body is eſteemed, according as he values himſelf.</item>
                  <item>A chip of the old block.</item>
                  <item>A rouling ſtone gathers no Moſſe.</item>
                  <item>An empty bag cannot ſtand upright.</item>
                  <item>A virtuous mind, and an honeſt hand, carries a man all over the world.</item>
                  <item>All that's given to a fool, is caſt away.</item>
                  <item>A ſmall rain allayes a great wind.</item>
                  <item>A cask, and an ill cuſtom, muſt be broken.</item>
                  <item>At length the Fox is brought to the Furrier.</item>
                  <item>A guilty conſcience is evermore ſuſpicious, and full of fear.</item>
                  <item>A man had better have a Knave, then a fool, to his Servant.</item>
                  <item>A young Serving-man, and old begger.</item>
                  <item>A fat Houſe-keeper makes a lean Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutor.</item>
                  <item>A ſilent tongue, and a true heart, did never any hurt to a Servant.</item>
                  <item>A man is known by his Wine, by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115502:13"/>his anger, and by his money.</item>
                  <item>A young man idle, and old man needy.</item>
                  <item>A gazing and gadding maid, ſeldome proves good Houſe-wife.</item>
                  <item>A Gentlemans Grayhound, and a Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>box, ſeek them at the fire.</item>
                  <item>A diſarmed Peace, is weak.</item>
                  <item>Aſtrology is true, but the Aſtrologers cannot find it.</item>
                  <item>At the Gmes end we ſhall ſee who wins.</item>
                  <item>A holy habit cleareth not a foul ſoul.</item>
                  <item>A little labour, much health.</item>
                  <item>A ſeaſonable gathering, and a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſpending, makes a good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping.</item>
                  <item>A flatterers throat, is an open Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre.</item>
                  <item>A good renoun is better then a golden girdle.</item>
                  <item>A maid often ſeen is a garment often worn.</item>
                  <item>An old wiſe mans ſhaddow, is better then a young buzzards ſword.</item>
                  <item>A mans Houſe is his Caſtle.</item>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115502:13"/>
                  <item>A hat is not made for one ſhower.</item>
                  <item>A covetous man is never rich.</item>
                  <item>Aſſail who will the valiant attends.</item>
                  <item>An idle youth makes a needy old age.</item>
                  <item>A ſad houſe where the hen crows louder then the cock.</item>
                  <item>A poor mans life is ſecure from harm.</item>
                  <item>A man may be deceived when he thinks himſelf moſt ſure.</item>
                  <item>A gift much expected, is paid not given.</item>
                  <item>An old Phyſician and a young Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer.</item>
                  <item>A little wind kindles much, puts out a fire.</item>
                  <item>A ſcepter is one thing and a ladle ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                  <item>A great dowry is a bed full of bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</item>
                  <item>A ſleepy Maſter makes his Servant a lout.</item>
                  <item>Afflictions are ſent us by God for our good.</item>
                  <item>Adverſity makes men wiſe.</item>
                  <item>A man without money is a body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life.</item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115502:14"/>
                  <item>A ſnow year a rich year.</item>
                  <item>A penny ſpared is twice got.</item>
                  <item>A ſmall heart hath ſmall deſires.</item>
                  <item>A pleaſure long expected is deer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſold.</item>
                  <item>A tyrant is moſt tyrant to himſelf.</item>
                  <item>A Trade is better then Service.</item>
                  <item>All beaſts of prey are ſtrong or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous.</item>
                  <item>An ill agreement is better then a good judgment.</item>
                  <item>A piece of a Church-yard fits many a mans body.</item>
                  <item>A Jade eats as much as a good Horſe.</item>
                  <item>An ill deed cannot bring honour.</item>
                  <item>A little given ſeaſonable excuſeth a great gift.</item>
                  <item>An old mans ſtaff is the rapper at deaths door.</item>
                  <item>An Ox is taken by the hornes a man by his tongue.</item>
                  <item>All that ſhakes falls not.</item>
                  <item>An old cat ſports not with her prey.</item>
                  <item>After death the Doctor.</item>
                  <item>All the arms in <hi>England</hi> will not arm fear.</item>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115502:14"/>
                  <item>A fair day in Winter is Mother of a Storm.</item>
                  <item>A man is known to be mortal by ſleep and luſt.</item>
                  <item>A mans deſtiny is alwaies dark.</item>
                  <item>A great Ship askes deep waters.</item>
                  <item>A wiſe man need not bluſh for chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his purpoſe.</item>
                  <item>An examined enterprize goes on boldly.</item>
                  <item>A good Sallet the beginning of a bad Supper.</item>
                  <item>A drunkards purſe is a bottle.</item>
                  <item>A Garden ſhould be dreſt and look't to as the body.</item>
                  <item>A dog ſcalded with hot water is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward afraid of cold.</item>
                  <item>A pittifull Mother makes a ſcab'd daughter.</item>
                  <item>A diſorder begets another.</item>
                  <item>An old ſin a new pennance.</item>
                  <item>A wall without a croſs, a Knight with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money, is abuſed by every one.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115502:15"/>
            </div>
            <div n="B" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>BEware the Geeſe when the Fox preaches.</item>
                  <item>Before you make a friend, eat a buſhell of Salt with him.</item>
                  <item>Blind men can judge no colours.</item>
                  <item>Better fed then taught.</item>
                  <item>Between the hand and the lip the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is loſt.</item>
                  <item>Baſtards by chance are good, by nature bad.</item>
                  <item>Birds of a feather will flock together.</item>
                  <item>Bad words finds bad acceptance.</item>
                  <item>Better a ſnoty child then his noſe wipt off.</item>
                  <item>Black will take no other hew.</item>
                  <item>Brag's a good dog.</item>
                  <item>Bate me an ace, quoth <hi>Bolton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Burnt child dreads the fire.</item>
                  <item>By Peace plenty.</item>
                  <item>Batchelers Wives, and Maides Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are well taught.</item>
                  <item>By ſcratching and biting cats and dogs comes together.</item>
                  <item>By ſhaving a fool many learn to ſheare.</item>
                  <item>By wiſdome Peace.</item>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115502:15"/>
                  <item>Black Ox hath not trod on his foot.</item>
                  <item>Be it better be it worſe, be rul'd by him that beares the purſe.</item>
                  <item>Beat the dog before the Lyon.</item>
                  <item>Bare walls makes giddy houſewifes.</item>
                  <item>Believe well and have well.</item>
                  <item>Beggers ſhould be no chooſers.</item>
                  <item>By Suppers more have been kil'd then <hi>Galen</hi> ever cur'd.</item>
                  <item>Build caſtles in the ayre.</item>
                  <item>Better fill a gluttons belly then his eye.</item>
                  <item>Better a bare foot then none.</item>
                  <item>Better be envyed then pittied.</item>
                  <item>Better eye out then half awake.</item>
                  <item>Better children weep then old men.</item>
                  <item>Building and marrying of children are great waſters.</item>
                  <item>Beauty draws more then Oxen.</item>
                  <item>Be as it may is no banning.</item>
                  <item>Better ſpare to have of thine own then ask others.</item>
                  <item>Better fed then taught.</item>
                  <item>Better late then never.</item>
                  <item>Building is chargeable.</item>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115502:16"/>
                  <item>Bread with holes, cheeſe without holes, and wine that ſparkles into the eyes, are the beſt.</item>
                  <item>Better ſpeak truth rudely then lye co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertly.</item>
                  <item>Bells call others, but themſelves enter not into the Church.</item>
                  <item>Better leave then lack.</item>
                  <item>Better ſuffer ill then do ill.</item>
                  <item>Bear with evil and expect good.</item>
                  <item>Building is a ſweet impoveriſhing.</item>
                  <item>Better half a loaf then no bread.</item>
                  <item>Beware of had-I-wiſt.</item>
                  <item>Bad Husbands are as neceſſary in a Common-wealth as good.</item>
                  <item>Between two ſtooles the tayl comes to the ground.</item>
                  <item>Better be an old mans darling, then a young mans warling.</item>
                  <item>Better a bad excuſe then none at all.</item>
                  <item>Buy a horſe ready man'd but a Wife unmand.</item>
                  <item>Brabling curs never want ſoar ears.</item>
                  <item>Better unborn then untaught.</item>
                  <item>Better the feet ſlip then the tongue.</item>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115502:16"/>
                  <item>Benefits pleaſe like flowers when they are freſh.</item>
                  <item>By doing nothing we learn to do ill.</item>
                  <item>Be what thou wouldſt ſeem to be.</item>
                  <item>Better to rule then be ruled by the rout.</item>
                  <item>Better to bow then break.</item>
                  <item>Better come to the latter end of a Feaſt then the beginning of a fray.</item>
                  <item>Better be half hang'd then ill wed.</item>
                  <item>Better to be happy then wiſe.</item>
                  <item>Better ſpare at brim then bottom.</item>
                  <item>Baſhfulneſſe is a ſign of grace.</item>
                  <item>Before thou marry have thy dwelling houſe.</item>
                  <item>Beauty is no heritage.</item>
                  <item>Better is an egge in peace then an Ox in war.</item>
                  <item>Better a louſe in the Pot then no fleſh at all.</item>
                  <item>Better ſit ſtill then riſe and fall.</item>
                  <item>Better one bird in the hand then ten in the wood.</item>
                  <item>By biting and ſcratching the Cat is with Kitlin.</item>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115502:17"/>
                  <item>Better good afar off then ill near at hand.</item>
                  <item>Buy at a Fair but ſell at home.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="C" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>CHildren and fools tell the truth.</item>
                  <item>Cuſtome is a ſecond nature.</item>
                  <item>Can Jackanapes be merry when his dog is at his heels?</item>
                  <item>Children learn to creep before they go.</item>
                  <item>Criticks are like bruſhers of noble mens cloathes.</item>
                  <item>Caſtles are Fortreſſes of ſtone.</item>
                  <item>Counſell without a cure, is a body without a ſoul.</item>
                  <item>Courting and wooing brings dallying and doing.</item>
                  <item>Curſt cows have ſhort hornes.</item>
                  <item>Cunning is no burthen.</item>
                  <item>Covetouſneſs breaks the bag.</item>
                  <item>Cut your coat according to your cloath.</item>
                  <item>Cat after kind.</item>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115502:17"/>
                  <item>Cities ſeldom change Religion only.</item>
                  <item>Courteſie on one only ſide laſts not long.</item>
                  <item>Cloudy mornings turn to clear even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</item>
                  <item>Civil Wars of <hi>France</hi> made a million of Atheiſts and 30000 Witches.</item>
                  <item>Cruelty is more cruel if we defer the pain.</item>
                  <item>Children when little, makes Parents fools, when great mad.</item>
                  <item>Compariſons are odious.</item>
                  <item>Cloſe ſits my ſhirt but cloſer my skin.</item>
                  <item>Chriſtmas comes but once a year.</item>
                  <item>Cloathes adorn Poules.</item>
                  <item>Change of paſture makes fat calves.</item>
                  <item>Children and chickens are alwaies a feeding.</item>
                  <item>Care brings gray hairs.</item>
                  <item>Change of Women make bald knaves.</item>
                  <item>Conſcience is hanged up long ago.</item>
                  <item>Claw a churl by the arſe, and he will ſhite in thy face.</item>
                  <item>Cloath thee in War, arm thee in Peace.</item>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115502:18"/>
                  <item>Counſell breaks not the head.</item>
                  <item>Craft againſt craft makes no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</item>
                  <item>Civility gains more then ſtrength of armes.</item>
                  <item>Coyne moves men to rage.</item>
                  <item>Converſation makes one what he is.</item>
                  <item>Corn is cleaned with wind the ſoul with chaſtenings.</item>
                  <item>Cover your ſelf with your Shield and care not for cryes.</item>
                  <item>Chuſe none for thy ſervant who hath ſerv'd thy betters.</item>
                  <item>Change of Countrey, change of Fortune.</item>
                  <item>Conditions breaks Laws.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115502:18"/>
            </div>
            <div n="D" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>DO well and have well.</item>
                  <item>Dally not with money nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</item>
                  <item>Diſgraces are like cherries one draws another.</item>
                  <item>Deadly heavy and full of ſinne.</item>
                  <item>Dancing follows a full belly.</item>
                  <item>Deſires torments us and hope com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for us.</item>
                  <item>Dear bought and far fetcht is good for Ladyes.</item>
                  <item>Danger it ſelf is the beſt remedy for danger.</item>
                  <item>Dogs barking a loof bite not at hand.</item>
                  <item>Dinner cannot be long where dainties are wanting.</item>
                  <item>Divine aſhes are better then earthly meat.</item>
                  <item>Deſires are nouriſht by delay.</item>
                  <item>Drink after grief goes merrily down.</item>
                  <item>Death and the Grave make no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of perſons.</item>
                  <item>Dogs begin in jeſt and end in earneſt.</item>
                  <item>Deceive not thy Phyſician, Confeſſor or Lawyer.</item>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115502:19"/>
                  <item>Dry bread is better at home then roaſt-meat abroad.</item>
                  <item>Divine grace was never flow.</item>
                  <item>Drought never brought a dearth.</item>
                  <item>Do what thou ought and come what can.</item>
                  <item>Diſcreet Women have neither keys nor ears.</item>
                  <item>Do well for others yet look to your ſelf.</item>
                  <item>Debtors are lyers.</item>
                  <item>Diſeaſes of the eyes are to be tured with the elbow.</item>
                  <item>Dearths foreſeen come not.</item>
                  <item>Dayes are fine in the field.</item>
                  <item>Death keeps no Callender.</item>
                  <item>Deeds are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Males words are Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115502:19"/>
            </div>
            <div n="E" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>EVery one that is in black is not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not a Scholar.</item>
                  <item>Evening words are not like to morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</item>
                  <item>Every houſe in <hi>Malagon</hi> hath a thief of his own.</item>
                  <item>Every mile is two in Winter.</item>
                  <item>Enough is as good as a Feaſt.</item>
                  <item>Every one faſtens where there is gain.</item>
                  <item>Every dog is a Lyon at home.</item>
                  <item>Even reckonings make long friends.</item>
                  <item>Every Ape. thinks his Puppy the faireſt.</item>
                  <item>Every mans conſcience is firſt moulded in his own nature.</item>
                  <item>Every one puts his fault on the times.</item>
                  <item>Expectation torments.</item>
                  <item>Ever ſince we wear cloathes, we know not one another.</item>
                  <item>Every cock is proud on his own dung hill.</item>
                  <item>Either wealth is much increaſed, or moderation is much decayed.</item>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115502:20"/>
                  <item>Every man cannot hit the nail on the head.</item>
                  <item>Ever ſpare and ever bare.</item>
                  <item>Ever drunk ever dry.</item>
                  <item>Every fool will be medling.</item>
                  <item>Early-pricks that will be a thorne.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eſſex</hi> ſtiles, <hi>Kentiſh</hi> miles, <hi>Norfolk</hi> wiles, many men beguiles.</item>
                  <item>Eaten bread is forgot.</item>
                  <item>Every one is not merry that dances.</item>
                  <item>Every one is King in his own houſe.</item>
                  <item>Every one hath a foole in his ſleeve.</item>
                  <item>Every thing is of uſe to a Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper.</item>
                  <item>Every thing new is fine.</item>
                  <item>Every man is bound to have a good conſcience.</item>
                  <item>Every one is witty for his own pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</item>
                  <item>Every Bees Honey is ſweet.</item>
                  <item>Every one as ſhe liketh, quoth the good woman when ſhe kiſt her Cow.</item>
                  <item>Every man baſteth the fat hog.</item>
                  <item>Every one after his own faſhion.</item>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115502:20"/>
                  <item>Empty veſſels ſound moſt.</item>
                  <item>Every man cannot be honeſt that would.</item>
                  <item>Every one can rule a ſhrew ſave he that hath her.</item>
                  <item>Evil gotten goods never prove well.</item>
                  <item>Every man for himſelf and God for us all.</item>
                  <item>Eat a peck of ſalt with a man before you truſt him.</item>
                  <item>Every thing helps, quoth the Wren when ſhe piſt in the Sea.</item>
                  <item>Every day brings its bread with it.</item>
                  <item>Evil will never ſaid well.</item>
                  <item>Empty Chambers makes fooliſh maides.</item>
                  <item>Every man hath his ill day.</item>
                  <item>Every labour will have its reward.</item>
                  <item>Even ſome old Foxes are taken in the ſnare.</item>
                  <item>Every Fox loves a Hen-ruſt.</item>
                  <item>Every meddall hath its right ſide and its wrong.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115502:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115502:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115502:22"/>
            </div>
            <div n="F" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>FIne words dreſſe ill deeds.</item>
                  <item>For one pleaſure a thouſand ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows.</item>
                  <item>For waſhing his hands none ſells his Lands.</item>
                  <item>Fair words makes me look to my Purſe.</item>
                  <item>From good men comes goodneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Fear nothing but ſin.</item>
                  <item>Fools live poor to die rich.</item>
                  <item>Fortune to one is a mother, another a ſtep-mother.</item>
                  <item>Favour will as ſurely periſh as life.</item>
                  <item>Few words and many deeds is beſt.</item>
                  <item>Fools bite one another but wiſe men agree together.</item>
                  <item>Fooliſh tongues talk by the douzen.</item>
                  <item>Fair is not fair but that which pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</item>
                  <item>Fair language grates not the tongue.</item>
                  <item>Fair feathers makes fair fowles.</item>
                  <item>Far fetcht and dear bought is good for Ladyes.</item>
                  <item>For a deſperate debt take any ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</item>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115502:22"/>
                  <item>From a fooliſh Judge a quick ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</item>
                  <item>Fiſh without wine is poyſon.</item>
                  <item>Far ſhooting never kil'd bird.</item>
                  <item>Fools have Fortune.</item>
                  <item>Fools are wiſe as long as ſilent.</item>
                  <item>For poor men to keep places for their pleaſure is their ruine.</item>
                  <item>Few words to the wiſe ſuffice.</item>
                  <item>Flies are buſieſt about lean Horſes.</item>
                  <item>Firſt come firſt ſerved.</item>
                  <item>Fair words and large promiſes pacifie anger.</item>
                  <item>From a cholerick man withdraw a little, from him that ſayes nothing for ever.</item>
                  <item>Firſt diſerve and then deſire.</item>
                  <item>Foul in the Cradle proveth fair in the ſaddle.</item>
                  <item>Fooles lade the water and wiſe men catch the fiſh.</item>
                  <item>Faint heart never woon fair Lady.</item>
                  <item>Fears are divided in the midſt.</item>
                  <item>Fare and ſoftly goes farre.</item>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115502:23"/>
                  <item>Fools ſet ſtooles for wiſe folks to ſtumble at.</item>
                  <item>Few Lawyers die well.</item>
                  <item>Faſt bind faſt find.</item>
                  <item>Fair without foul within.</item>
                  <item>Firſt creep then go.</item>
                  <item>Froſt and fraud have alwaies foul ends.</item>
                  <item>From three things God keep us, from Powder'd-beef without muſtard, from a ſervant that vieweth himſelf, a wife that is painted.</item>
                  <item>France is a medow that cuts thrice a year.</item>
                  <item>Fools with fair words are pleaſed.</item>
                  <item>Few Phyſicians live well.</item>
                  <item>Full of courteſie full of craft.</item>
                  <item>Fair words hurts not the mouth.</item>
                  <item>Foul water will quench fire as well as fair.</item>
                  <item>Fiſh muſt ever ſwimme twice.</item>
                  <item>Folly it is to ſpurn againſt a prick.</item>
                  <item>From women light and liquoriſh, good fortune ſtill deliver us.</item>
                  <item>Forſake not the Market for the tolle.</item>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115502:23"/>
                  <item>Forbear not fowing becauſe of Birds.</item>
                  <item>Folly grows without watering.</item>
                  <item>Four good Mothers beget four bad Daughters, Great familiarity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Truth hatred, Virtue envy, Riches ignorance.</item>
                  <item>For the ſame man to be a heretique and a good Subject is impoſſible.</item>
                  <item>Fair dreſſing is a foul houſe ſwept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the door.</item>
                  <item>Fools give to pleaſe all but their own.</item>
                  <item>Frenzy, hereſie, and jealouſie ſeldom cured.</item>
                  <item>From my friends God defend me, from my enemies I can keep my ſelf.</item>
                  <item>Firſt come to the Mill firſt grinde.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115502:24"/>
            </div>
            <div n="G" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>GOod to be merry and wiſe.</item>
                  <item>God ſends meat the Devil ſends cooks.</item>
                  <item>Give a dog roaſt and beat him with the ſpit.</item>
                  <item>Good words are worth much and coſt little.</item>
                  <item>Good words quench more then a bucket of water.</item>
                  <item>Gaming Women and Wine, whileſt they laugh make men pine.</item>
                  <item>Give a Woman what ſhe ſhould have, and what ſhe would have, and ſhe will be quiet.</item>
                  <item>Great rie and little wool.</item>
                  <item>Give an inch and you will take an ell.</item>
                  <item>Good cloathes put a man in heart.</item>
                  <item>God ſendeth cold after cloathes.</item>
                  <item>Great ſtrokes makes not ſweet mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</item>
                  <item>Good workmen are ſeldome rich.</item>
                  <item>Govern the mouth by the eſtate.</item>
                  <item>Gifts enter every where without a Wimble.</item>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115502:24"/>
                  <item>God ſends coole according to cloathes.</item>
                  <item>God ſendeth fortune to fools.</item>
                  <item>Great fortune brings with it great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune.</item>
                  <item>Good words coſt nought.</item>
                  <item>Great boaſt ſmall roaſt.</item>
                  <item>God never ſendeth mouthes but he ſendeth meat.</item>
                  <item>Gameſters drink and Fidlers Wives are free for all commers.</item>
                  <item>Good Wine needs no buſh.</item>
                  <item>Good cheap commodities are notable pick-purſes.</item>
                  <item>God gives his wrath by weight and without weight his mercy.</item>
                  <item>God ſends curſt Cows ſhort hornes.</item>
                  <item>Good riding at two Anchors if one fail the other will hold.</item>
                  <item>God ſends corn the Devil makes the ſack.</item>
                  <item>Great is the Harveſt the abundant gather.</item>
                  <item>Gods ſecrets are concealed from men</item>
                  <item>Gameſters and Race-horſes never laſt long.</item>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115502:25"/>
                  <item>Great allowing leſſens no mans living.</item>
                  <item>Good ſtomack needs no ſauce.</item>
                  <item>Good news may be told at any time, but ill in the morning.</item>
                  <item>Green wood makes a hot fire.</item>
                  <item>Goods are theirs that enjoy them.</item>
                  <item>Gods Mill grindes ſlow but ſure.</item>
                  <item>Give a clown your finger and he will take your hand.</item>
                  <item>Good ſervice is a great enchantment.</item>
                  <item>Good is to be ſought out and evil at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</item>
                  <item>God is at the end when we think he is furtheſt of.</item>
                  <item>Good and quickly ſeldom meet.</item>
                  <item>Good fortune ſtill delivers any.</item>
                  <item>Good reſtorers make good lenders.</item>
                  <item>God heals and the Phyſician hath the thankes.</item>
                  <item>God rewardeth the obedient.</item>
                  <item>God, our Parents, and our Maſters can never be requited.</item>
                  <item>God favoureth and defendeth the wronged.</item>
                  <item>Great paines quickly finds eaſe.</item>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115502:25"/>
                  <item>God comes to ſee without a Bell.</item>
                  <item>God complains not but doth what is fitting.</item>
                  <item>Give looſers leave to talk.</item>
                  <item>Great deformers grow intollerable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumers.</item>
                  <item>God oft hath a great ſhare in a little houſe.</item>
                  <item>God keep me from four Houſes, a Uſurers, a Tavern, a Spittle, and a Priſon.</item>
                  <item>God provides for him that truſteth.</item>
                  <item>Giving much to the poor, doth increaſe a mans ſtore.</item>
                  <item>God in the tongue, and the Devil in the heart.</item>
                  <item>Gluttony kils more then the Sword.</item>
                  <item>Great trees are good for nothing but ſhade.</item>
                  <item>Giving is dead reſtoring very ſick.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115502:26"/>
            </div>
            <div n="H" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>HOney is ſweet but the Bee ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</item>
                  <item>He that ſtrikes with his tongue muſt ward with his head.</item>
                  <item>He that marries for wealth ſells his Liberty.</item>
                  <item>He that tels his wife news is but newly married.</item>
                  <item>He that hath a Fox for his mate had need have a net at his girdle.</item>
                  <item>He that is not handſome at twenty, nor ſtrong at thirty, nor rich at fourty, nor wiſe at fifty, will never be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, ſtrong, rich or wiſe.</item>
                  <item>He ſits not ſure, that ſits too high.</item>
                  <item>He who will know what he is worth, let him not be ſurety.</item>
                  <item>He that marries late marries ill.</item>
                  <item>Hearken to Reaſon or ſhe will be heard.</item>
                  <item>He truly begins to dye that quits his chief deſire.</item>
                  <item>He hath great need of a fool that will play the fool himſelf.</item>
                  <item>Half a loaf is better then no bread.</item>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115502:26"/>
                  <item>He that goes a borrowing goes a ſorrowing.</item>
                  <item>He that bewailes his want hath beg'd ſufficiently.</item>
                  <item>He that ſtumbles and fals not mends his pace.</item>
                  <item>He that will live in Peace and reſt, muſt hear, and ſee, and ſay the beſt.</item>
                  <item>He that gainſayes not gives his full conſent.</item>
                  <item>He hath enough that's pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
                  <item>He that doth fight with ſilver is ſure to overcome.</item>
                  <item>He that cannot paye let him pray.</item>
                  <item>He is leaſt worthy of honour that ſeeks it.</item>
                  <item>Hazard little to gain much.</item>
                  <item>He that corrects not ſmall faults, cannot controle great ones.</item>
                  <item>He that hath one eye is a King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the blind.</item>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115502:27"/>
                  <item>He will play at ſmall game before he will ſtand out.</item>
                  <item>He that lies down with dogs muſt riſe with fleas.</item>
                  <item>He playes well that winnes.</item>
                  <item>He ſpeaks me fair but wiſhes my throat cut.</item>
                  <item>He dotes more then a fool on his bable.</item>
                  <item>He that is man'd by Boyes, and horſt with Colts, ſhall have his meat eaten, and his work undone.</item>
                  <item>He that lives well is learn'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</item>
                  <item>He that hath not wherewithall to eat hath ſtore of ſorrows.</item>
                  <item>He that will take the Bird let him not ſcare it.</item>
                  <item>He is an Aſſe that hurts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</item>
                  <item>He muſt needs ſwim that is held up by the chin.</item>
                  <item>He that will learn to pray let
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115502:27"/>him go to Sea.</item>
                  <item>Hold with the Hare and run with the Hound.</item>
                  <item>He that wants money wants all things.</item>
                  <item>He is doubly fond that ſatisfies his fondneſſe.</item>
                  <item>He that ſees what's good, and takes what is bad, is a wilfull fool.</item>
                  <item>He deſerveth not to give Laws, who cannot endure to receive them.</item>
                  <item>Hungry dogs will eat durty Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</item>
                  <item>He may weep till his heart ake that hath no body comfort him.</item>
                  <item>He that ſends a Sea, is ſure to looſe his Venture.</item>
                  <item>He hears with one ear that is deaf with the other.</item>
                  <item>He that eats Cherries with his Love picks not the beſt.</item>
                  <item>He that contemplates hath a day
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115502:28"/>without a night.</item>
                  <item>He that dares not truſt to his hand had beſt to truſt to his feet.</item>
                  <item>He is a very Aſſe that thinks to live ever.</item>
                  <item>He muſt needs go that the Devil drives.</item>
                  <item>He that is warm thinks all ſo.</item>
                  <item>He who hath but one daies felicity is unhappy all the year.</item>
                  <item>He thinks not well that thinks not again.</item>
                  <item>He barks at the Moon that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to diſparage truth.</item>
                  <item>Half warn'd half arm'd.</item>
                  <item>He that hopes for dead mens ſhooes may go long bare-foot.</item>
                  <item>He that ſtudies his contentment o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch ever wants it.</item>
                  <item>He caſts a miſt before a mans eyes that puts money in his hand.</item>
                  <item>Hunger will break through ſtone walls.</item>
                  <item>He that hath ſpice may ſeaſon as he liſt.</item>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115502:28"/>
                  <item>He dances well to whom fortune pipes.</item>
                  <item>He ſpent <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Rent in <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſommer</hi> Quarter.</item>
                  <item>He hath an oare in every mans boate.</item>
                  <item>He hath many Irons in the fire.</item>
                  <item>He ſhall be call'd a Fool to his face, That doing well will quit his place.</item>
                  <item>He is an Aſſe that cannot make uſe of his own.</item>
                  <item>He that will have a Hare to break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt muſt hunt over night.</item>
                  <item>He that is at eaſe ſeeks vanities.</item>
                  <item>He knows on which ſide his bread is buttered on.</item>
                  <item>He is a good markſman that aims at the heel and hits the head.</item>
                  <item>He that mounteth higher then he ought ſhall deſcend lower then he would.</item>
                  <item>He that miſchief hatcheth miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief catcheth.</item>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115502:29"/>
                  <item>He loſeth nothing that loſeth not God.</item>
                  <item>He that gives a Capon give him him the leg and the wing.</item>
                  <item>He that doth that he ought not, that happens to him that he thinks not.</item>
                  <item>How can the Fole amble when the Horſe and Mare trot?</item>
                  <item>Honour is troubleſome.</item>
                  <item>He that playes his money ought to value it.</item>
                  <item>He beginneth to build to ſoon that hath not money to finiſh it.</item>
                  <item>He that is angry at a Feaſt is rude.</item>
                  <item>He ſhall never have a thing good cheap that is afraid to ask the price.</item>
                  <item>He that is angry is not at eaſe.</item>
                  <item>Haſt makes waſte.</item>
                  <item>He mends as four Ale mends in Summer.</item>
                  <item>He that hath times and looks for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115502:29"/>time loſeth time.</item>
                  <item>He that hath hornes in his boſome let him not put them on his head.</item>
                  <item>He is an ill Husband that is not miſt.</item>
                  <item>He can ill pipe that lacks his upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip.</item>
                  <item>He that is afraid of every graſſe, muſt not piſſe in a Medow.</item>
                  <item>He throughly puniſhes that loves throughly.</item>
                  <item>He never loved well that hated for a trifle.</item>
                  <item>He that loves another better then himſelf ſtarves in a Cooks Shop.</item>
                  <item>He is a fool that throws at his heel what he hath in his hand.</item>
                  <item>Half a word is enough to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Reader.</item>
                  <item>He that hath a fame of riſing early may ſleep till dinner.</item>
                  <item>He that will eat the kernell let him crack the nur.</item>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115502:30"/>
                  <item>He looſeth the Market for the tolle.</item>
                  <item>He goes far that never returns.</item>
                  <item>He that lives ill fear follows him.</item>
                  <item>Hunger and ſhame are mortal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</item>
                  <item>He that ſends a fool means to follow him.</item>
                  <item>He is as blind as a beetle.</item>
                  <item>He hath a leaden head and a wooden wit.</item>
                  <item>He that winketh with one eye, and ſeeth with the other, I will not truſt him though he were my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                  <item>He ſtands not ſurely that never ſlipt.</item>
                  <item>Health is a Jewell.</item>
                  <item>Hell is full of good meanings and wiſhings.</item>
                  <item>He that ſees his neighbours houſe a fire muſt look to his own.</item>
                  <item>He that ſoweth good ſeed ſhall reap good Corn.</item>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115502:30"/>
                  <item>He holds his Noſe to the Grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</item>
                  <item>He that is born to be hang'd ſhall never be drown'd.</item>
                  <item>Hot love ſoon cold.</item>
                  <item>He is handſome that hanſdome doth.</item>
                  <item>Happy is he that Chaſtens himſelf.</item>
                  <item>He that ſtayes does the buſineſſe.</item>
                  <item>Hold faſt when you have it.</item>
                  <item>Hope well and have well.</item>
                  <item>He had need have a long ſpoon that eat with the Devil.</item>
                  <item>Happy is he that owes nothing.</item>
                  <item>He leaves a place well that leaves a Friend in it.</item>
                  <item>He that hath much ſhall have more.</item>
                  <item>Hauger pierces ſtone-walls.</item>
                  <item>Health without money is half a ſickneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Honour is unſeemly for a fool.</item>
                  <item>His body is better cloathed then his ſoul.</item>
                  <item>He would make you believe the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115502:31"/>Moon is made of green Cheeſe.</item>
                  <item>He is mad that quarrels with wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Beaſts.</item>
                  <item>He hath a conſcience as large as a Franſiſcans ſleeve.</item>
                  <item>He may ill run that cannot go.</item>
                  <item>He that reckons without his hoſt muſt reckon twice.</item>
                  <item>He is happy that can be warn'd by others harms.</item>
                  <item>Hunger hath alwaies a good Cook.</item>
                  <item>He makes a mountain of a mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill.</item>
                  <item>He that goes far gains much.</item>
                  <item>He maketh a long harveſt of a little Corn.</item>
                  <item>He is fool-hardy.</item>
                  <item>He that looſeth his wife and ſix pence hath loſt a Teaſter. <hi>Fr.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>He that hath an ill Name is half Hang'd.</item>
                  <item>He that kils a man when he is drunk, ſhall be hang'd when he is ſober.</item>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115502:31"/>
                  <item>Home is home when all is done, or be it never ſo poor.</item>
                  <item>Honours ſhould change manners.</item>
                  <item>He doth little that doth not afford his hand as well as his head.</item>
                  <item>He that lies long abed his Eſtate feels it.</item>
                  <item>Handſome women without Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, finds more ſweet-hearts then Husbands.</item>
                  <item>Hunger is the beſt ſauce.</item>
                  <item>He that lives in hope danceth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out muſick.</item>
                  <item>He that will live long, muſt keep his mouth coole, his feet warm and dry.</item>
                  <item>He that will not when he may,</item>
                  <item>When he will he ſhall have nay.</item>
                  <item>He that never drank was never adry.</item>
                  <item>He that is angry without a cauſe, muſt be pleaſed without amends.</item>
                  <item>He that will meddle with all things, may go ſhooe the Gooſe.</item>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115502:32"/>
                  <item>He ſweares like an Abbot.</item>
                  <item>He that buyes a houſe ready built hath many a pin and nayl for nought.</item>
                  <item>He that leaves God, God will leave him.</item>
                  <item>He that will not do ill muſt look well to himſelf.</item>
                  <item>He that Riſeth firſt is firſt dreſt.</item>
                  <item>He is proper that hath proper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</item>
                  <item>He that looks not before finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf behind.</item>
                  <item>He that playes more then he ſees, forfeits his eyes to the King.</item>
                  <item>Huſty counſell ſeldom profitable.</item>
                  <item>He that loves the tree loves the branch.</item>
                  <item>He is to haſty to be a Pariſh Clerk.</item>
                  <item>He is as ſharp as a thorn.</item>
                  <item>He is more buſie then he hath thankes for his labour.</item>
                  <item>He that hath not enough hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</item>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115502:32"/>
                  <item>He gets enough that looſeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</item>
                  <item>He that hath told good news need tell no more.</item>
                  <item>He is an aſſe that gives fleſh for bones.</item>
                  <item>He that ſtriketh with the ſword, ſhall be beaten with the ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard.</item>
                  <item>Humble hearts have humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</item>
                  <item>He that goes bare-foot muſt not plant thornes.</item>
                  <item>He that hath right hath courage.</item>
                  <item>He that makes himſelf aſleep the Wolf ſhall catch him.</item>
                  <item>He pulls with a long Rope that waits for anothers death.</item>
                  <item>He that will revenge all wrongs ſhall ſooner end himſelf then them.</item>
                  <item>He begins to die that quits his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</item>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115502:33"/>
                  <item>He that gets out of debt grows rich.</item>
                  <item>He that is truly hungry, will not ſtick to eat any thing.</item>
                  <item>He that is faulty turns coward.</item>
                  <item>He laugheth that winneth.</item>
                  <item>He that eates the hard ſhall eat the ripe.</item>
                  <item>Haſte makes waſt.</item>
                  <item>Here's a talk of the Turk and the Pope, but my next neighbour doth me more harm then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                  <item>He that comes laſt makes all faſt.</item>
                  <item>He that worſt payes ſhall hold the Candle.</item>
                  <item>He is no body.</item>
                  <item>He ſtands for a Cipher.</item>
                  <item>He that deceives me once, it is his faul; if twice, it is mine.</item>
                  <item>He ſcornes the motion.</item>
                  <item>He that will not berul'd by his own dame, muſt be rul'd by his ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame,</item>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115502:33"/>
                  <item>He over-looks him as the Devil look't over <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>He that cannot diſſemble knows not how to live.</item>
                  <item>Hatred with Friends is ſuccour to foes.</item>
                  <item>He gets in the hundred but looſeth in the ſhire.</item>
                  <item>He gives others good counſell but takes none himſelf.</item>
                  <item>He that hath plenty of goods ſhall have more.</item>
                  <item>He puls an old Houſe on his head.</item>
                  <item>He is in a peck of troubles.</item>
                  <item>Honour without profit is a Ring on the finger.</item>
                  <item>He that will be ſerv'd muſt be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</item>
                  <item>He that doth what he will doth not what he ought.</item>
                  <item>He that hath loſt his credit is dead to the world.</item>
                  <item>He that hath no ill fortune is troubled with good.</item>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115502:34"/>
                  <item>He that takes not up a pin ſlights his his Wife.</item>
                  <item>He that looſeth his due gets not thanks.</item>
                  <item>He that demands miſſeth not unleſſe his demands be fooliſh.</item>
                  <item>He that blames would buy.</item>
                  <item>He that once deceives is ever ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected.</item>
                  <item>He is a fool that brags of four things; Good wine, a handſome Wife, a handſome Horſe, and good ſtore of money.</item>
                  <item>He that makes a good War makes a good Peace.</item>
                  <item>He that hath love on his breaſt hath Spurres on his ſides.</item>
                  <item>He that reſpects not is not reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</item>
                  <item>He that ſpeaks ſowes, and he that holds his Peace gathers.</item>
                  <item>He that hath one hog makes him fat, and he that hath but one Son makes him a fool.</item>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115502:34"/>
                  <item>Hope is the poor mans bread</item>
                  <item>He that's long a giving knows not how to give.</item>
                  <item>He that tells a ſecret is anothers ſervant.</item>
                  <item>Help thy ſelf and God will help thee.</item>
                  <item>He that commits a fault thinks eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſpeaks of it.</item>
                  <item>He that lives well one year ſorrows ſeven year after.</item>
                  <item>He that truſts in a lye ſhall periſh in truth.</item>
                  <item>He that riſeth betimes hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his head.</item>
                  <item>He is a fool that thinks not that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinks.</item>
                  <item>Hunger drawes a Wolf out of the Forreſt.</item>
                  <item>He that burns his houſe warms him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf once.</item>
                  <item>He ſpends ill that ſpends a whole years rent at one meal.</item>
                  <item>He is not poor that hath little
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115502:35"/>but he that deſires much.</item>
                  <item>He wrongs not an old man that ſteales his Supper from him.</item>
                  <item>He that labours and thrives ſpins gold.</item>
                  <item>He that ſoweth truſteth in God.</item>
                  <item>He that is fooliſh in the thought let him be wiſe in the puniſhment.</item>
                  <item>He that hath no good Trade it is to his loſſe.</item>
                  <item>Happier are the hands compaſt with iron then the heart with thoughts.</item>
                  <item>He that lends gives.</item>
                  <item>Haſt comes not alone.</item>
                  <item>He looks not well to himſelf that looks not ever.</item>
                  <item>He can give little to his Servant that locks his knife.</item>
                  <item>He that can ſtay obtains.</item>
                  <item>He that gives all before he dies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides to ſuffer.</item>
                  <item>He that hath not his Craft let him ſhut up ſhop.</item>
                  <item>He that mocks a Cripple ought to be whole.</item>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115502:35"/>
                  <item>He that goes far hath many encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</item>
                  <item>He that cockers his child provides for his enemy.</item>
                  <item>He is not free that draws his chain.</item>
                  <item>He that keeps his own makes War.</item>
                  <item>He that endures is not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</item>
                  <item>He that talkes much of happineſſe ſummons grief.</item>
                  <item>He that knows nothing doubts no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</item>
                  <item>He that paſſeth a Winters day e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapes an enemy.</item>
                  <item>He that is his own Counſellor knows nothing ſure but what he hath laid out.</item>
                  <item>He hath not liv'd that lives not after death.</item>
                  <item>He that learns a Trade, hat a purchaſe made.</item>
                  <item>He that is at eaſe ſeeks dainties.</item>
                  <item>He that ſowes intends to reap.</item>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115502:36"/>
                  <item>He that is in a Tavern thinks he is in a Vine Garden.</item>
                  <item>He that is ſurprized with the firſt Froſt feels it all the Winter after.</item>
                  <item>He that followes the Lord hopes to go before.</item>
                  <item>He that gives me ſmall gifts would have me live.</item>
                  <item>He that hath Laws hath quarrels.</item>
                  <item>He that ſteales an egge will ſteal an Oxe.</item>
                  <item>Half the world knows not how the other half lyes.</item>
                  <item>He that is a Maſter muſt ſerve ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                  <item>He is a fool that goes afoot for the eaſe of his horſe.</item>
                  <item>He a beaſt muſt die that hath done no good to his Countrey.</item>
                  <item>He that is not in the Wars is not out of danger.</item>
                  <item>He that goes to bed thirſty riſeth healthy.</item>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115502:36"/>
                  <item>Heaven is not to be got with wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                  <item>He that will do thee a good turn, either he will be gone or die.</item>
                  <item>He that is once born, once muſt die.</item>
                  <item>He that makes himſelf aſleep muſt be eat by the Wolves.</item>
                  <item>He that's afraid of leaves goes not to the wood.</item>
                  <item>Happineſſe cannot be attain'd in this world.</item>
                  <item>Health and wealth makes mens lives comfortable.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115502:37"/>
            </div>
            <div n="I" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>IT is better to give one Shilling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way way then lend twenty.</item>
                  <item>In a womans Garment is her va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</item>
                  <item>It is a ſhame to ſteal but a worſe to carry home.</item>
                  <item>Ill gotten ill ſpent.</item>
                  <item>In love is no lack.</item>
                  <item>Ill gotten goods never thrive.</item>
                  <item>If the Wiſe erred not it would go hard with the fool.</item>
                  <item>Ill putting a naked ſword in a mad mans hand.</item>
                  <item>It is not good to hold a Candle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the duell.</item>
                  <item>In truſt is Treaſon.</item>
                  <item>In a good houſe all is quickly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</item>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115502:37"/>
                  <item>Ill weeds grow apace.</item>
                  <item>It's better to ſee a clout then a hole out.</item>
                  <item>If things were to be done twice all would be wiſe.</item>
                  <item>Jack would be a Gentleman if he could ſpeak French.</item>
                  <item>It is better to be envyed then pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
                  <item>It's abſurd to warm one in his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</item>
                  <item>In ſpending lies the advantage.</item>
                  <item>In a hundred ells of contention there is not one inch of love.</item>
                  <item>If every man would mend one all would mend.</item>
                  <item>It's a great trouble to ride and death to foot it.</item>
                  <item>It's batter to buy then borrow.</item>
                  <item>It's as good to be in the dark as without light.</item>
                  <item>It is ill to ſet ſpurs to a flying horſe.</item>
                  <item>It is a foul Bird that fouls his own neſt</item>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115502:38"/>
                  <item>Ill egging makes ill begging.</item>
                  <item>It is eaſie to think a thing but hard to bring it about.</item>
                  <item>It is better to be ſpited then pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied.</item>
                  <item>It is better to ſtand idle then to perform a thing idly. <hi>Ital.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>It's better to ſtrike a man on the back then on the belly.</item>
                  <item>It's no ſporting with edg's tooles.</item>
                  <item>In ſpace cometh grace.</item>
                  <item>It's good to have ſome friends both in heaven and hell.</item>
                  <item>In time comes ſhe whom God ſends.</item>
                  <item>It chanceth in an hour that comes not in ſeven years.</item>
                  <item>It's an ill wind blows no man good.</item>
                  <item>It's a good horſe never ſtumbles.</item>
                  <item>Ill news comes to ſoon.</item>
                  <item>It is not good jeſting with edg'd tooles.</item>
                  <item>Ill gotten goods ſoon waſte.</item>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115502:38"/>
                  <item>In the Husband wiſdom, in the Wife gentleneſſe.</item>
                  <item>It's better to bow then break.</item>
                  <item>If you would know ſecrets, look them in grief or pleaſure.</item>
                  <item>If the Mother had never been in the Oven ſhe had never look't for her daughter there.</item>
                  <item>It's the beſt part of a fool to ſay, I had not thought.</item>
                  <item>In life you love me not, in death you bewail me.</item>
                  <item>If every man had is own he would be as rich as a new ſhorn ſheep.</item>
                  <item>It ſtaineth lik the durt of <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>It's bad cloth will take no colour.</item>
                  <item>It's eaſier to come into debt then pay a debt.</item>
                  <item>It's an ill counſell hath no miſcape.</item>
                  <item>It cometh by kind, it coſt them nothing.</item>
                  <item>It's better to kiſſe a knave then be troubled with him.</item>
                  <item>Ill ware is never cheap.</item>
                  <item>It's better to be unborn then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught.</item>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:115502:39"/>
                  <item>It's better to be a ſhrew then a ſheep.</item>
                  <item>It's an ill dog not worth the whiſtling.</item>
                  <item>Ill veſſels ſeldom miſcarry.</item>
                  <item>I ſcratch where it itcheth not.</item>
                  <item>It's eaſier to deſcend then aſcend.</item>
                  <item>If it were a Bear it would bite you.</item>
                  <item>It's ill waking of a ſleeping dog.</item>
                  <item>It is true that all men ſay.</item>
                  <item>It's hard ſtriving againſt a ſtream.</item>
                  <item>It's ill healing of an old ſore.</item>
                  <item>It muſt needs be true that every man ſaith.</item>
                  <item>Ill gotten goods what becomes of them?</item>
                  <item>If the ſtaff be crooked the ſhadow cannot be ſtraight.</item>
                  <item>It's good ſleeping in a whole skin.</item>
                  <item>It's to late to grieve when the chance is paſt.</item>
                  <item>It is ill ſhaving againſt the wool.</item>
                  <item>Ill luck is good for ſomething.</item>
                  <item>If the Lyons skin can't do it the Foxes ſhall.</item>
                  <item>Ill comes in by ells and goes out by inches.</item>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115502:39"/>
                  <item>It's ill halting before a Cripple.</item>
                  <item>It's merry in hall when beards wag all.</item>
                  <item>It's an ill bird defiles his own neſt.</item>
                  <item>If wiſhes were Thruſhes then begger s would eat Birds.</item>
                  <item>I had rather ride on a horſe that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries me then an Aſſe that throws me.</item>
                  <item>It's good fiſhing in troubled waters.</item>
                  <item>In good years corn is hay, in ill years ſtraw is corn.</item>
                  <item>It's good to beware by other mens harmes.</item>
                  <item>It's better late then never.</item>
                  <item>If you would know a knave give him a ſtaff.</item>
                  <item>It's good to have a hatch before the door.</item>
                  <item>It's a long journey from the tongue to the hand.</item>
                  <item>It's an eaſie matter to find a ſtaff to beat a dog.</item>
                  <item>Ill company is the authour of all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</item>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115502:40"/>
                  <item>It's hard to wive and thrive both in a year.</item>
                  <item>It's merry when Knaves meet.</item>
                  <item>If you looſe your time you cannot get money.</item>
                  <item>It is not all butter that the cow ſhites.</item>
                  <item>I wept when I was born, and every day ſhews why.</item>
                  <item>It is hard to teach an old dog tricks.</item>
                  <item>It is better to give the fleece then the wool.</item>
                  <item>In vain does the mill clack if the Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler his hearing lack.</item>
                  <item>It is hard to keep that which is deſired by many.</item>
                  <item>In chooſing a Wife and buying a a ſword, we ought not truſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                  <item>It's a good horſe never ſtumbles.</item>
                  <item>I may ſpeak for what I paid for.</item>
                  <item>If the blind lead the blind both will fall into the ditch.</item>
                  <item>I was taken by a morſell, ſaies the fiſh.</item>
                  <item>If thou mindeſt to be Pope, thou muſt have him to write in thy forehead.</item>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115502:40"/>
                  <item>It will not out of the fleſh that is bred in the bone.</item>
                  <item>Ill natures, the more you ask them the more they ſtick.</item>
                  <item>It's impoſſible to avoid deſtiny.</item>
                  <item>I will not buy a Pig in a poake.</item>
                  <item>In every Art it is good to have a maſter.</item>
                  <item>It's too much to find ſalve and lint.</item>
                  <item>Ill never ſpake well.</item>
                  <item>If fools went not to market all wares would be kept.</item>
                  <item>In love there is both dotage and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion.</item>
                  <item>In time men get experience.</item>
                  <item>It is worſe to be bad then to be thought ſo.</item>
                  <item>If great men would have care of little ones, both would laſt long.</item>
                  <item>It is not alwaies fair wheather.</item>
                  <item>I give my mouſe a hole and ſhe will become my heir.</item>
                  <item>It is not good to have an oare in every ones boat.</item>
                  <item>It is better to be the head of Pike
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115502:41"/>then the tail of a Sturgeon.</item>
                  <item>In a hundred pound of Law there is not a half-penny weight of love.</item>
                  <item>Infants manners are moulded more by the Parents example then by the ſtars of their nativity.</item>
                  <item>It's god to ſtrike while the iron is hot.</item>
                  <item>In the morning mountains in the evening fountains.</item>
                  <item>If you could run as you drink you might catch a hare.</item>
                  <item>It's not good fiſhing before the net.</item>
                  <item>In a long journey ſtraw wares.</item>
                  <item>It's more pain to do nothing then ſomething.</item>
                  <item>It's a wicked thing to make a dearth ones Gardner.</item>
                  <item>If the brain ſows not corn it plant thiſtles.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115502:41"/>
            </div>
            <div n="K" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>KNowledge makes one laugh but wealth makes one dance.</item>
                  <item>Kiſſing goes by favour.</item>
                  <item>King <hi>Henry</hi> Loud a man.</item>
                  <item>Kiſſe my arſe is but a poor comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                  <item>Kick not againſt a prick.</item>
                  <item>Ka me and I'le ka thee.</item>
                  <item>Kindneſſe will creep where it cannot go.</item>
                  <item>Knaves and fools are the compoſition of the whole world.</item>
                  <item>Kill two Birds with one ſtone.</item>
                  <item>Knowledge is no burthen.</item>
                  <item>Keep good men company and you ſhall be of the number.</item>
                  <item>Keep the Wolf from the door.</item>
                  <item>Keep your eye off writings and your hand out of other mens pockets.</item>
                  <item>Kind words are currant money at ſometimes.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115502:42"/>
            </div>
            <div n="L" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>LEt him laugh that wins.</item>
                  <item>Look not too high leſt a chip fall in thine eye.</item>
                  <item>Love is potent but money is omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</item>
                  <item>Leſſon after leſſon makes good Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</item>
                  <item>Love is not without bitterneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Love cometh in at the window and goeth out at the door.</item>
                  <item>Long Jeſtings are never good.</item>
                  <item>Little pot ſoon hot.</item>
                  <item>Love overcomes nothing but a ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart.</item>
                  <item>Lightly come lightly go.</item>
                  <item>Loſſe imbraces ſhame.</item>
                  <item>Like the Flounder, out of the frying-pan into the fire.</item>
                  <item>Love your neighbour, yet pull not down your hedge.</item>
                  <item>Love is blind.</item>
                  <item>Let the world ſay what they will if I find all well at home.</item>
                  <item>Little wealth little care.</item>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115502:42"/>
                  <item>Little knoweth the fat ſow what the lean doth mean.</item>
                  <item>Love makes all hard things gentle.</item>
                  <item>Little good ſoon ſpent.</item>
                  <item>Leaves enough but few Grapes.</item>
                  <item>Let a hen live though ſhe hath the pip.</item>
                  <item>Leave jeaſting whileſt it pleaſeth, leſt it come to earneſt.</item>
                  <item>Love me little love me long.</item>
                  <item>Little dogs ſtart the hare, the great one get lier.</item>
                  <item>Love doth much but money doth all.</item>
                  <item>Look ere you leap.</item>
                  <item>Love me, love my dog.</item>
                  <item>Love rules his Kingdom without a ſword.</item>
                  <item>Love askes faith and faith firmneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Lawyers houſes are built on the heads of fools.</item>
                  <item>Lovers live by love as Larks by leeks.</item>
                  <item>Look not for musk in a dogs Kennel.</item>
                  <item>Let every man meddle with his own.</item>
                  <item>Like maſter like man.</item>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115502:43"/>
                  <item>Love is the true price of love.</item>
                  <item>Life is half ſpent before we know what it is.</item>
                  <item>Lean not to a broken ſtaff.</item>
                  <item>Love makes one fit for any work.</item>
                  <item>Little ſaid ſoon amended.</item>
                  <item>Love and buſineſſe find eloquence.</item>
                  <item>Love is not found in the Market.</item>
                  <item>Love and a cough cannot be hid.</item>
                  <item>Longs more to marrage the four bare legs in a bed.</item>
                  <item>Learn weeping and thou ſhalt laugh gaming.</item>
                  <item>Let all live as they would die.</item>
                  <item>Like a chip in pottage doth neither good nor harm.</item>
                  <item>Like will to like.</item>
                  <item>Life without a friend is death without witneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Long abſent ſoon forgotten.</item>
                  <item>Love and Lordſhip abides no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</item>
                  <item>Let every one his own burden bear.</item>
                  <item>Leave a fool alone and he will bethink what he hath to do.</item>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115502:43"/>
                  <item>Love warms more then a thouſand fiers.</item>
                  <item>Liberty is a Jewel.</item>
                  <item>Look not a given horſe in the mouth.</item>
                  <item>Let not him that fears feathers come. among wild-fowels.</item>
                  <item>Light a Candle before the devill.</item>
                  <item>Little pitchers have wide eares.</item>
                  <item>Leave is light.</item>
                  <item>Let an ill man lie in thy ſtraw and he looks to be thy heir.</item>
                  <item>Light gaines makes a heavy Purſe.</item>
                  <item>Light burthens long born grow hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy.</item>
                  <item>Lay no Pearl before ſwine.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="M" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>MUch water goes by the Mill the Miller knows not of.</item>
                  <item>Many Lords many Laws.</item>
                  <item>Money breeds rage love marriage.</item>
                  <item>Meaſure is a merry mean.</item>
                  <item>Modeſty is the mother of good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</item>
                  <item>Money anſwers all things.</item>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:115502:44"/>
                  <item>Many things are loſt for want of asking.</item>
                  <item>More afraid then hurt.</item>
                  <item>Money begets money.</item>
                  <item>Much cry and little wool.</item>
                  <item>Man purpoſeth God diſpoſeth.</item>
                  <item>Might overcometh right.</item>
                  <item>My houſe, my houſe, though thou art ſmall thou art to me Eſcuriall.</item>
                  <item>Much would have more.</item>
                  <item>Many ſpeak much that cannot ſpeak well.</item>
                  <item>Much babling is not without offence.</item>
                  <item>Much travelling makes bad wayes.</item>
                  <item>Many a good cow hath an ill calf.</item>
                  <item>Make haſt in an ill way to get out of it.</item>
                  <item>Many Kinsfolk few friends.</item>
                  <item>Men ſpeak of the fare as things went with them there.</item>
                  <item>Many hands makes light work.</item>
                  <item>My Kill of Malt is on fire.</item>
                  <item>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sfortunes ſeldom come alone.</item>
                  <item>Miſreckoning is no payment.</item>
                  <item>Man will ſtrive hard for profit.</item>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:115502:44"/>
                  <item>Many a little makes a mickle.</item>
                  <item>Money refuſed looſeth his brightneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Make hay while the Sun ſhines.</item>
                  <item>Marry your Son when you will, your daughter when you can.</item>
                  <item>Money cheereth mans heart.</item>
                  <item>More haſt worſt ſpeed.</item>
                  <item>Marry a Widow before ſhe leaves mourning.</item>
                  <item>Many cannot ſee wood for trees.</item>
                  <item>Mend your cloathes and you may hold out this year.</item>
                  <item>Man hath nothing that is his, not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</item>
                  <item>Many kiſſe the child for the nurſes ſake.</item>
                  <item>Misfortunes are burthens hard to be born.</item>
                  <item>Many a man talkes of little <hi>John</hi> that never did him know.</item>
                  <item>More ſauce than meat.</item>
                  <item>Many ſmall make a great.</item>
                  <item>Mention not a halter in the houſe of him that was hang'd.</item>
                  <item>Much profit cannot be made in poor towns.</item>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115502:45"/>
                  <item>Make a page of your own age.</item>
                  <item>Many ſpeak of <hi>Robbin Hood</hi> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhot in his bow.</item>
                  <item>Married to day ſad to morrow.</item>
                  <item>Make a pipe of a pigges tayl.</item>
                  <item>Money wants no followers.</item>
                  <item>Men are not meaſured by the yard or ell.</item>
                  <item>Many things are loſt for want of asking.</item>
                  <item>Marriage and hanging goes by deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</item>
                  <item>Many kiſſe the hand they wiſh cut off.</item>
                  <item>Moſt men ſalure the wronged man.</item>
                  <item>Make not a balk of good ground.</item>
                  <item>Moſt maſter wear the breeches.</item>
                  <item>Mills and Wives ever want.</item>
                  <item>Men muſt make there market as the time ſerves.</item>
                  <item>Man ought to be humble not proud.</item>
                  <item>Milk ſayes to Wine, Welcome Friend.</item>
                  <item>Many ſtumble ar a ſtraw and leape o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a block.</item>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:115502:45"/>
                  <item>Marry your daughters betimes leſt they marry themſelves.</item>
                  <item>Malice never ſpeaks well.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="N" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>NO Alchimy to ſaving.</item>
                  <item>Never pleaſure without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</item>
                  <item>No love to a Fathers.</item>
                  <item>No cheat like the religious cheat.</item>
                  <item>No longer pipe no longer dance.</item>
                  <item>No fence for ill fortune.</item>
                  <item>Nothing ſo certain as death.</item>
                  <item>New Objects breed new thoughts.</item>
                  <item>Not length of daies but ſtrength of heart rids the work.</item>
                  <item>Need hath no Law.</item>
                  <item>No lock will hold againſt the power of gold.</item>
                  <item>Need makes the old Wife trot.</item>
                  <item>Never had ill workman good rooles.</item>
                  <item>New Lords new Laws.</item>
                  <item>Nothing but money is moneys worth.</item>
                  <item>No dearth but breeds in the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manger.</item>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:115502:46"/>
                  <item>Neither bribe nor loſe thy right.</item>
                  <item>No man loves his fetters though they be of gold.</item>
                  <item>None knowes the weight of anothers burthen.</item>
                  <item>Nothing venture, nothing have.</item>
                  <item>No Writer can pleaſe all.</item>
                  <item>None ſo great an enemy as he of ones own trade.</item>
                  <item>No man ought to look a guift Horſe in the mouth.</item>
                  <item>Night is the Mother of Counſels.</item>
                  <item>Nothing is impoſſible to a willing mind.</item>
                  <item>No pride like an inricht begger.</item>
                  <item>No butter will ſtick on his Bread.</item>
                  <item>No envy like a Monkes.</item>
                  <item>Near is my petticoat but nearer is my ſmock.</item>
                  <item>Novelties pleaſe women.</item>
                  <item>No ſmoak but there is ſome fire.</item>
                  <item>None is a fool alwaies, every one ſometimes.</item>
                  <item>Nothing hath no ſavour.</item>
                  <item>No body deceived but he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fides.</item>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115502:46"/>
                  <item>None ſaies his Garner is full.</item>
                  <item>No ſooner is a Temple built to God, but the Devil hath his Chappell hard by.</item>
                  <item>Nature draws more then ten teemes.</item>
                  <item>Never yet that man that every one ſpake well of.</item>
                  <item>Nothing is to be preſumed of nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaired of.</item>
                  <item>No Church-yard ſo handſome as a man would deſire ſtraight to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried there.</item>
                  <item>Neceſſity is the beſt Schoolmiſtriſſe.</item>
                  <item>Nothing dries ſooner then teares.</item>
                  <item>Nothing laſts but the Church.</item>
                  <item>No Barber ſhaves ſo cloſe but another finds work.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="O" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>ONe may think what he dares not ſpeak.</item>
                  <item>One ſhrewd turn follows another.</item>
                  <item>Ones gettings orders ones ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</item>
                  <item>Of an ill pay-maſter never refuſe money.</item>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115502:47"/>
                  <item>One acre of poſſeſſion is worth a whole land of promiſe.</item>
                  <item>On a good bargain think twice.</item>
                  <item>One foot is better then two crutches.</item>
                  <item>Of ſufferance cometh eaſe.</item>
                  <item>One flower makes no Garland.</item>
                  <item>One beggers wo that another by the door ſhould go.</item>
                  <item>One ſound blow will ſerve to undo all.</item>
                  <item>One ill word asketh another.</item>
                  <item>One fore-warn'd as good as two.</item>
                  <item>Out of Gods bleſſing into the warm Sun.</item>
                  <item>Once a whore and alwaies a whore.</item>
                  <item>One muſt be a Servant before he can be a Maſter.</item>
                  <item>Once a Knave and ever a Knave.</item>
                  <item>One ſtroke fells not an Oake.</item>
                  <item>Of all ſmels bread of all taſtes ſalt.</item>
                  <item>One pair of heels worth two pair of hands.</item>
                  <item>One fool makes a hundred.</item>
                  <item>One regards more the will then the deed.</item>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:115502:47"/>
                  <item>One Wolf will not bite another.</item>
                  <item>Of a good beginning comes a good ending.</item>
                  <item>One good turn askes another.</item>
                  <item>One journey and two errands. <hi>Ital.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>One ſwallow makes no Summer.</item>
                  <item>Of young men there dies many of old men ſcapes not any.</item>
                  <item>One day Caſh-keeper the next ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheir'd.</item>
                  <item>Of little medling cometh great eaſe.</item>
                  <item>Out of debt out of danger.</item>
                  <item>One may eaſily find a ſtaff to beat a dog.</item>
                  <item>Out of ſight out of mind.</item>
                  <item>One ſlumber finds another.</item>
                  <item>One ill weed marres a whole pot of pottage.</item>
                  <item>One mouth doth nothing without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</item>
                  <item>Old wine and an old friend are good proviſions.</item>
                  <item>On painting and fighting look afar of.</item>
                  <item>Opportunity is whoredomes baud.</item>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115502:48"/>
                  <item>One may viſit a friend ſometimes, but if he intends to be welcome he muſt not ſtay long.</item>
                  <item>One may ſee day at a little hole.</item>
                  <item>One tongue is enough for a woman.</item>
                  <item>Opportunity makes a thief.</item>
                  <item>Our own actions are our ſecurity, not others Judgments.</item>
                  <item>One beateth the buſh and another catcheth the Bird.</item>
                  <item>One pair of ears is enough to dry up an hundred tongues.</item>
                  <item>Often and little eating makes a man fat.</item>
                  <item>Old men go to death, death comes to young men.</item>
                  <item>Out nettle in dock.</item>
                  <item>Out of the frying-pan into the fire.</item>
                  <item>One enemy is too much.</item>
                  <item>One ſword keeps another in the ſheath.</item>
                  <item>One ſwallow makes not a Summer, nor one Woodcock a Winter.</item>
                  <item>Offer not to preſent ſalt or the head of any creature.</item>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115502:48"/>
                  <item>Old men and far travellers may lye by authority.</item>
                  <item>One hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſleep before midnight is worth three after.</item>
                  <item>Old Birds are not caught with chaff.</item>
                  <item>One fair day in Winter makes not birds merry.</item>
                  <item>Often under a mean habit is hid a fine Treaſure.</item>
                  <item>One ſeldom loſes by dealing with honeſt men.</item>
                  <item>One ſcab'd ſheep will marre a whole flock.</item>
                  <item>One hair of benevolence draws more then a hundred yoak of Oxen.</item>
                  <item>Of fair things the autume is fair.</item>
                  <item>Once at eaſe and ever a cuſtom.</item>
                  <item>Old men when they ſeem young make much of death.</item>
                  <item>Once a year a man may ſay on his conſcience.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115502:49"/>
            </div>
            <div n="P" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>PLeaſure long expected is dear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough bought</item>
                  <item>Play, a Whore, and brisk Wine, make a man poor laughing.</item>
                  <item>Promiſing is the eye of giving.</item>
                  <item>Play with a fool at home and he will play with you abroad.</item>
                  <item>Preferment choaks.</item>
                  <item>Pardons and pleaſantneſſe are great revenges of ſlanders.</item>
                  <item>Poor and proud, fy fy.</item>
                  <item>Prettineſſe dies firſt.</item>
                  <item>Pain is forgotten where gain follows.</item>
                  <item>Perverſneſſe makes one ſquint-ey'd.</item>
                  <item>Penny wiſe and pound fooliſh.</item>
                  <item>Poverty is the Mother of health.</item>
                  <item>Pride goes before ſhame cometh after.</item>
                  <item>Praiſe a hill but keep low.</item>
                  <item>Pride will have a fall.</item>
                  <item>Pleaſure and profit draws all the world.</item>
                  <item>Proffered ſervice ſtinks.</item>
                  <item>Pains to get, care to keep, fear to looſe.</item>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:115502:49"/>
                  <item>Puniſhment is lame but it comes.</item>
                  <item>Preſents of love fear not to be ill taken of ſtrangers.</item>
                  <item>Prove thy friend ere thou have need.</item>
                  <item>Poor and liberall rich and covetous.</item>
                  <item>Puff not againſt the wind.</item>
                  <item>Penſions never enricht young man.</item>
                  <item>Poverty is no ſinne.</item>
                  <item>Prejudicial friendſhip let it go with a vengeance.</item>
                  <item>Peeviſh pity marres a City.</item>
                  <item>Phyſician cure thy ſelf.</item>
                  <item>Praiſe none too much for all are fickle.</item>
                  <item>Pillow Counſell proves vain.</item>
                  <item>Praiſe a fair day at night.</item>
                  <item>Princes are Veniſon in Heaven.</item>
                  <item>Pretended holineſſe is double iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
                  <item>Providence is better then a rent.</item>
                  <item>Pouring oyl into the fire is not the way to quench it.</item>
                  <item>Prayers and provender hinder no jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</item>
                  <item>Parſons are fools Waggoners.</item>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:115502:50"/>
                  <item>Pleaſing ware is half ſold.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="Q" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>QUick at Victuals quick at work.</item>
                  <item>Quick believers need broad ſhoulders.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="R" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>REady money is a ready medicine.</item>
                  <item>Rich Land muſt not be left for a greedy Landlore.</item>
                  <item>Rivers need a ſpring.</item>
                  <item>Rivers ſwell not with clear water.</item>
                  <item>Revenge is ſweet.</item>
                  <item>Riches have wings.</item>
                  <item>Rouling ſtones gather no moſſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> was not built in one day.</item>
                  <item>Rob <hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Reckoners without their hoſt muſt reckon twice.</item>
                  <item>Remove an old tree and it will die.</item>
                  <item>Rich men are like Whales, for they grow great by the ruine of others.</item>
                  <item>Raw leather will ſtretch.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115502:50"/>
            </div>
            <div n="S" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>SHe ſpins well that breeds her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</item>
                  <item>Sorrow is alwaies dry.</item>
                  <item>Set a Knave to catch a Knave.</item>
                  <item>Save a thief from the Gallows and he will cut your throat.</item>
                  <item>Sep after ſtep the Ladder's aſcended.</item>
                  <item>Seldome comes a better.</item>
                  <item>So many men in Court ſo many ſtrangers.</item>
                  <item>Saying and doing are two things.</item>
                  <item>So many Countries ſo many cuſtoms.</item>
                  <item>Self do ſelf have.</item>
                  <item>Shew me a lyer and I'le ſhew thee a thief.</item>
                  <item>Seldome ſeen is ſoon forgotten.</item>
                  <item>Say no ill of the year till it be paſt.</item>
                  <item>Shame in a kindred cannot be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
                  <item>Some make a conſcience of ſpitting in the Church yet rob the Altar.</item>
                  <item>So long goes the pot to the water that at laſt it comes home broken.</item>
                  <item>Service is no Inheritance.</item>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115502:51"/>
                  <item>Shamefull craving muſt have ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nay.</item>
                  <item>Skill and confidence are an unconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Army.</item>
                  <item>Small pitchers have wide ears.</item>
                  <item>Such a Saint ſuch an offering.</item>
                  <item>Set a begger on Horſeback and he will gallop.</item>
                  <item>Soft fire makes ſweet malt.</item>
                  <item>Soon gotten ſoon ſpent.</item>
                  <item>Such Carpenters ſuch Ships.</item>
                  <item>Sad is he that ſtands between the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and the hammer.</item>
                  <item>Spit in your hands and take better hold.</item>
                  <item>Short ſhooting loſeth the game.</item>
                  <item>Short maſſe and long dinner.</item>
                  <item>So many heads ſo many wits.</item>
                  <item>Silke doth quench the fire in the Kitchin.</item>
                  <item>Somewhat is better then nothing.</item>
                  <item>Soon hot ſoon cold.</item>
                  <item>Sweet meat will have ſour ſauce.</item>
                  <item>Sleep without Supper wake without owing.</item>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115502:51"/>
                  <item>Stumble at a ſtraw and leap over a block.</item>
                  <item>Speak fitly or be ſilent wiſely.</item>
                  <item>Sweet diſcourſe makes ſhort daies and nights.</item>
                  <item>Sound love is not ſoon forgotten.</item>
                  <item>See for love and buy for money.</item>
                  <item>Soon ripe ſoon rotten.</item>
                  <item>Still fiſheth he that catcheth one.</item>
                  <item>Souldiers in Peace are like chimneys in Summer.</item>
                  <item>Speak fair and think what you will.</item>
                  <item>Such a Father ſuch a Son.</item>
                  <item>Science is nought worth without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</item>
                  <item>Spend and God will ſend.</item>
                  <item>Such lips ſuch lettice.</item>
                  <item>Silkes and ſattins put ont the fire in the chimney.</item>
                  <item>Such welcome ſuch farewell.</item>
                  <item>Spare and ever bare.</item>
                  <item>Sins are not known till they are act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
                  <item>Stop two gaps with one buſh.</item>
                  <item>Speak not of my debts unleſſe you
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115502:52"/>mean to pay them.</item>
                  <item>States have their Periods as well as bodies.</item>
                  <item>Send a wiſe man on an errand and ſay nothing to him.</item>
                  <item>Spare to ſpeak and ſpare to ſpeed.</item>
                  <item>Store is no ſore.</item>
                  <item>Such a one hath a good wit if a wiſe man had the keeping of it.</item>
                  <item>Ships fear fire more then water.</item>
                  <item>Struggle not againſt the ſtream.</item>
                  <item>Stay a while that we may make an end the ſooner.</item>
                  <item>Such beginning ſuch end.</item>
                  <item>Small invitation will ſerve a begger.</item>
                  <item>Still ſow eates all the draff.</item>
                  <item>Serve a noble man though poor the time comes that he will repay thee.</item>
                  <item>Spectacles are deaths Harquebuze.</item>
                  <item>Shame take him that ſhame thinks.</item>
                  <item>Service without reward is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                  <item>Some had rather looſe their friend then their jeaſt.</item>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:115502:52"/>
                  <item>Slander is a ſhipwrack by a dry tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt.</item>
                  <item>Some men plant an opinion they ſeem to eradicate.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="T" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>THe Citizen at his buſineſſe before he riſe.</item>
                  <item>The eyes have a language every where.</item>
                  <item>To ſpeak of a Uſerer at the Table marres the Wine.</item>
                  <item>To review ones ſtore is to mow twice.</item>
                  <item>Two falſe Knaves need no broker.</item>
                  <item>The eye is bigger then the belly.</item>
                  <item>The world is now adaies God ſave the Conqueror.</item>
                  <item>The death of Wolves is the ſafety of ſheep.</item>
                  <item>Thoſe that God loves don't live long.</item>
                  <item>Two heads are better then one.</item>
                  <item>The devil divides the world between Atheiſm and Superſtition.</item>
                  <item>The mouſe that hath but one hole is quickly taken.</item>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:115502:53"/>
                  <item>There's a Remedy for every thing could men find it.</item>
                  <item>There is an hour wherein a man might be happy all his life could he find it.</item>
                  <item>The effect ſpeaks the tongue need not.</item>
                  <item>To a child all weather is cold.</item>
                  <item>To him that will waies are not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                  <item>The Market is the beſt Garden.</item>
                  <item>Time undermines us.</item>
                  <item>The cholarick drinks, the melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eats, the phlegmatick ſleeps.</item>
                  <item>The deaf gaines the injury.</item>
                  <item>The dainties of the great are teares of the poor.</item>
                  <item>The Maſter abſent and the houſe dead.</item>
                  <item>The great put the little on the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Italians</hi> are wiſe before the deed, the <hi>Germans</hi> in the deed, the <hi>French</hi> after the deed.</item>
                  <item>The beſt bread have the beſt Portions.</item>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115502:53"/>
                  <item>Too much familiarity breeds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</item>
                  <item>The Spring for the eye but the fall for the mouth.</item>
                  <item>That which is bred in the bone will never out of the fleſh.</item>
                  <item>Truth may be blamed but it cannot be ſhamed.</item>
                  <item>To be too buſie gets contempt.</item>
                  <item>There is no fire without ſome ſmoak.</item>
                  <item>The good wan is the laſt that knows whats amiſſe at home.</item>
                  <item>To day in a poſture or ſhape to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in ones grave.</item>
                  <item>The Court hath no Almanack.</item>
                  <item>The worlds well amended with him.</item>
                  <item>There's not ſo great a flood but there's as low an ebbe.</item>
                  <item>The eye and Religion can bear no jeaſting.</item>
                  <item>There's no accord where every man would be a Lord.</item>
                  <item>The ſluggard loves alife things done to his hand.</item>
                  <item>There is no earthly gate, that an Aſſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115502:54"/>laden with money cannot enter.</item>
                  <item>The beſt of the ſport is to do the deed and ſay nothing.</item>
                  <item>There's no hill without it's valley.</item>
                  <item>The greateſt ſtate the leſſe ſure.</item>
                  <item>They that are bound muſt obey.</item>
                  <item>The Pox is a gentlemans companion.</item>
                  <item>The Woman had never lookt for her daughter in the Oven if ſhe had not been there her ſelf.</item>
                  <item>The firſt and the laſt froſt is the worſt.</item>
                  <item>The hearts letter is read in the eye.</item>
                  <item>Truſt no friend with that you need fear him if he were your enemy.</item>
                  <item>The defects are the mens not the arts.</item>
                  <item>The table robs more then a thief.</item>
                  <item>The new broom ſweeps clean.</item>
                  <item>The Wolf knows what the ill beaſt thinks.</item>
                  <item>The fearfull man never makes good Surgeon.</item>
                  <item>The ſnow for eight daies is a mother after a ſtep-mother.</item>
                  <item>The virtue of a coward is ſuſpition.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Germans</hi> wit is in his fingers.</item>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:115502:54"/>
                  <item>The devil never aſſails a man unleſſe he find him void of knowledge or the fear of God.</item>
                  <item>Take heed of ſtill water the quick paſſe away.</item>
                  <item>The nearer the Church the further from God.</item>
                  <item>The Corn hides it ſelf in ſnow as an old man in furs.</item>
                  <item>There's no body will go to hell for company.</item>
                  <item>The Jews ſpend at <hi>Easter,</hi> the Moors at marriage the Chriſtians in ſutes.</item>
                  <item>The love of money and the love of learning readily meet.</item>
                  <item>The wiſe hand doth not all the fooliſh mouth ſpeaks.</item>
                  <item>The horſe that is next the mill car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries all the griſt.</item>
                  <item>The more women look in the glaſſe the leſſe they look to their houſe.</item>
                  <item>The worſt of Law is that one ſute breeds twenty.</item>
                  <item>There are more men threatned then ſtriken.</item>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115502:55"/>
                  <item>The hard gives more then he that hath nothing.</item>
                  <item>The fool askes much but more he that grants it.</item>
                  <item>Three may keep counſell if two be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</item>
                  <item>The beaſt that goes alwaies never wants blows.</item>
                  <item>There is no fool to the old fool.</item>
                  <item>There is more talk then trouble.</item>
                  <item>There is difference betwixt ſtaring and ſtark mad.</item>
                  <item>The Fox knows much but more he that catcheth him.</item>
                  <item>Time and tyde ſtayes for no man.</item>
                  <item>There would be no great ones if there were no little ones.</item>
                  <item>The beſt mirrour is an old friend.</item>
                  <item>The tongue talkes at the heads caſt.</item>
                  <item>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not good language which all underſtands not.</item>
                  <item>The Child ſayes nothing but what it learn'd by the fire.</item>
                  <item>The abſent party is ſtill faulty.</item>
                  <item>Though you riſe early yet the day
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:115502:55"/>comes at his time and not till then.</item>
                  <item>There is falſhood in fellowſhip.</item>
                  <item>The fault is as great as he that is faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
                  <item>Time is the Rider that breaks youth.</item>
                  <item>The buyer needs a hundred eyes the ſeller one.</item>
                  <item>The dog that licks aſhes truſt not with meale.</item>
                  <item>The horſe thinks one thing and he that ſaddles him another.</item>
                  <item>The rought net is not the beſt catcher of fiſh.</item>
                  <item>There are three waies, the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Sea, the Court.</item>
                  <item>This world is nothing except it tend to another.</item>
                  <item>Thou haſt death in thy houſe and doſt bewail anothers.</item>
                  <item>The Prieſt hath forgotten that he was a Clark.</item>
                  <item>The morning Sun never laſts a day.</item>
                  <item>The comforters head never akes.</item>
                  <item>To a crazy Ship all winds are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</item>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:115502:56"/>
                  <item>Too much of one thing is good for nothing.</item>
                  <item>The reſolved mind hath no ears.</item>
                  <item>The bite of a ſheep never pierceth the skin.</item>
                  <item>The back door robs the houſe.</item>
                  <item>The Gown is his that wears it, and the world his that enjoys it.</item>
                  <item>Time ſtayeth for no man.</item>
                  <item>Things well fitted abide.</item>
                  <item>The Maſters eye fattens the horſe and his foot the ground.</item>
                  <item>Talk paies no tolle.</item>
                  <item>Touch a gall'd horſe on the back and and he will winch.</item>
                  <item>The tree that God plants no wind rents it.</item>
                  <item>Time paſt we can't recall.</item>
                  <item>The beſt workmen are commonly the worſt Husbands.</item>
                  <item>The toothach is more eaſe then to deal with ill people.</item>
                  <item>'Tis hard to be wretched but worſe to be known ſo.</item>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:115502:56"/>
                  <item>The charges of building and making of Gardens are unknown.</item>
                  <item>There's more maides then maukins.</item>
                  <item>Truſt not one nights ice.</item>
                  <item>Though you ſee a Churchman ill yet continue in the Church ſtill.</item>
                  <item>To gain teacheth how to ſpend.</item>
                  <item>There's more wayes to the wood then one.</item>
                  <item>The dog gnaws the bone becauſe he cannot ſwallow it.</item>
                  <item>The Sea hath fiſh for every man.</item>
                  <item>The good Mother ſayes not will you but gives.</item>
                  <item>Two eyes can ſee more then one.</item>
                  <item>The eye will have his part.</item>
                  <item>The firſt degree of folly is to hold ones ſelf wiſe, the ſecond to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, the third to deſpiſe counſell.</item>
                  <item>Truth ſhameth the Devil.</item>
                  <item>To weep for joy is a kind of Manna.</item>
                  <item>The Crow bewailes the ſheep, and eats it.</item>
                  <item>Tread on a worm and it will turn.</item>
                  <item>The firſt ſervice a child doth a Father is to make him fooliſh.</item>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:115502:57"/>
                  <item>The command of cuſtom is great.</item>
                  <item>Two ill meales makes the third a glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</item>
                  <item>True praiſe rootes and ſprouts.</item>
                  <item>The Cat ſees not the mouſe ever.</item>
                  <item>The fiſh adores the bait.</item>
                  <item>The Royal Crown cures not the headach.</item>
                  <item>There is great force hidden in a ſweet command.</item>
                  <item>The more thy years the nigher the grave.</item>
                  <item>The thread breaks where it is weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</item>
                  <item>The fat man knows not what the lean thinketh.</item>
                  <item>The ſlothfull is the Servant of a Priſon.</item>
                  <item>The more you ſtirre the more you ſtink.</item>
                  <item>Time is the Rider that breaks youth.</item>
                  <item>Two anons and a by and by is an hour and a half.</item>
                  <item>The perſwaſions of fortune ſwayes the doubtfull.</item>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:115502:57"/>
                  <item>Talk much and erre much, ſaies the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The ſight of a man hath the force of a Lyon.</item>
                  <item>Time and ſtraw makes medlers ripe.</item>
                  <item>The ballance diſtinguiſheth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween gold and ſilver.</item>
                  <item>There is no Colt but will break ſome halter.</item>
                  <item>The ſoul needs few things the body many.</item>
                  <item>The Reaſons of the poor weigh not.</item>
                  <item>To be beloved is above all bargains.</item>
                  <item>The evening praiſes the day.</item>
                  <item>To deceive ones ſelf is very eaſie.</item>
                  <item>The fair laſteth the whole year.</item>
                  <item>The eſcaped mouſe ever feels the taſt of the bait.</item>
                  <item>The back door makes the thief and whore.</item>
                  <item>The covetous ſpends more then the liberall.</item>
                  <item>The off-ſpring of the very old or very young laſts not.</item>
                  <item>There's no weather ill when the wind is ſtill.</item>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:115502:58"/>
                  <item>Too much taking heed is loſſe.</item>
                  <item>The reverend are ever before.</item>
                  <item>The firſt diſh pleaſeth all.</item>
                  <item>'Tis eaſier to build two Chimneys then to main tain one.</item>
                  <item>That groat is ill ſav'd that ſhames the Maſter.</item>
                  <item>Take heed of an Ox before, an horſe behind, of a Parſon on all ſides.</item>
                  <item>The greateſt crabs be not the beſt.</item>
                  <item>There are more Phyſicians in health then drunkards.</item>
                  <item>There's a craft in daubing.</item>
                  <item>The Wife is the key of the houſe.</item>
                  <item>The greateſt Clarks be not the wiſeſt men.</item>
                  <item>The leaſt fooliſh is wiſe.</item>
                  <item>The ſinging man keeps his ſhop in his throat.</item>
                  <item>The firſt blow is as much as two.</item>
                  <item>The life of a man is a Winter way.</item>
                  <item>The Phyſician ows all to the Patient, but the Patient ows him nothing but a little money.</item>
                  <item>There's not enough if nothing be loſt.</item>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:115502:58"/>
                  <item>To the counſell of fools a word is beſt.</item>
                  <item>To a fair day open your window.</item>
                  <item>The ignorant hath an Eagles wing and an Owles eye.</item>
                  <item>To a gratefull man give money when he askes.</item>
                  <item>The greateſt talkers are the leaſt doers</item>
                  <item>There's none ſo deaf as he that will not hear.</item>
                  <item>The higher the Ape goes the more he ſhews his tayl.</item>
                  <item>The Fox fares beſt when he is curſt.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Dutch</hi> have there wits in their hands.</item>
                  <item>The beſt may amend.</item>
                  <item>The chief diſeaſe that reignes this year is folly.</item>
                  <item>The ſcal'd head fears cold water.</item>
                  <item>Three things alwaies bring coſt, the fawning of a dog, the love of a whore, and the invitation of an hoſt.</item>
                  <item>There is no jeaſting either with ones eye or ones Religion.</item>
                  <item>The Horſe to the ſaddle, the Aſſe to the pack, the Ox to the plow, the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:115502:59"/>Dog to the chace, but man to that art which nature cals him to.</item>
                  <item>The year doth nothing elſe but open and ſhut.</item>
                  <item>The greedy fool that all would preſſe</item>
                  <item>The head of a woman, the body of a Serjant, the leggs of a Lackey, make a Devil perfect.</item>
                  <item>True honour is the Daughter of truth.</item>
                  <item>Truſt is the Mother of deceit.</item>
                  <item>The world is round, and he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſwim ſinks to the bottom.</item>
                  <item>The outſide of a woman is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the beſt.</item>
                  <item>The curious ſearcher finds himſelf unfortunate.</item>
                  <item>The honeſter man the worſer luck.</item>
                  <item>Two wits diſcern better then one.</item>
                  <item>Thoughts be free from tolle.</item>
                  <item>Troubles ſent from God are Jewels, but drawn on by our ſelves are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                  <item>The greateſt Calf is not the ſweeteſt Veal.</item>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:115502:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <item>Though the Sun ſhine leave not thy cloak at home.</item>
                  <item>Two pots well fill'd are ſigns of a Feaſt.</item>
                  <item>The end makes all equall.</item>
                  <item>The offender never pardons.</item>
                  <item>The higher I climb the greater my fall.</item>
                  <item>Travell whether thou canſt but die where thou oughteſt.</item>
                  <item>That which one learns in youth will continue till old age.</item>
                  <item>There is no ill which doth not turn to our good.</item>
                  <item>The mill gets by going.</item>
                  <item>The Cuckold is the laſt that knows it.</item>
                  <item>The Hoarding of money is both ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and caſual.</item>
                  <item>The skilfulleſt, wanting money, are but ſcorned.</item>
                  <item>Too crafty a Cur to be taken with this bone.</item>
                  <item>They that are booted are not alwaies ready.</item>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:115502:60"/>
                  <item>The Wife that bites her lips and treads askew is to her husband and her ſelf untrue.</item>
                  <item>The Sun that ſhineth early in the morning, a Woman that ſpeaketh lattin, and a Child that drinketh Wine, ſeldom make good end.</item>
                  <item>The wife and the ſword are to be ſhew'd not lent.</item>
                  <item>Teares in the eyes have ſorrow in the heart.</item>
                  <item>To day a merchant to morrow a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant.</item>
                  <item>The weakeſt goes to the walls.</item>
                  <item>The Chicken is the Countries but the City eats it.</item>
                  <item>The more rich the more honour.</item>
                  <item>Takes pepper in the noſe.</item>
                  <item>The wearer knows where the ſhooe wrings.</item>
                  <item>Too much ſcratching ſmarts, too much ſpeaking hurts.</item>
                  <item>The more knave the better luck.</item>
                  <item>To ſpeak well belongs to few, to live well belongs to all.</item>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:115502:60"/>
                  <item>The proof of the pudding is in the eating.</item>
                  <item>The gray mare is the better horſe.</item>
                  <item>That is not handſome which is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but that is handſome which takes.</item>
                  <item>Things well fitted abide.</item>
                  <item>They that know one another ſalute afar of.</item>
                  <item>The riſing of one man is the fall of another.</item>
                  <item>The good Wife of a wilfull man hath many a wofull day.</item>
                  <item>Think of eaſe but work on.</item>
                  <item>There's as many faſhions as folks.</item>
                  <item>The King of good-fellows is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Queen of beggers.</item>
                  <item>Truth and Oyl are ever above.</item>
                  <item>The Market-place the Rogues houſe.</item>
                  <item>There longs more to a wedding then four bare legs in a bed.</item>
                  <item>The tongue Walkes where the teeth ſpeed not.</item>
                  <item>The early Bird catcheth the worm.</item>
                  <item>The lame tongue gets nothing.</item>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:115502:61"/>
                  <item>There are many waies to fame.</item>
                  <item>The ſhorteſt anger is doing.</item>
                  <item>The toothach is more eaſie then love.</item>
                  <item>Three Women make a Market.</item>
                  <item>The wiſeſt man doth ſometimes play the fool.</item>
                  <item>The Pope comes by voices, the King by natue, the Emperour by force.</item>
                  <item>There are ſome that would be droun'd in a glaſſe of water.</item>
                  <item>The Goat muſt brouſe where ſhe is tied.</item>
                  <item>The houſe ſhews the owner.</item>
                  <item>The fool is moſt fuſty when he is leaſt fooliſh.</item>
                  <item>The rich devoure the poor, the ſtrong the weak.</item>
                  <item>The Smith and his penny both are black.</item>
                  <item>The dead are not to be mentioned at Board.</item>
                  <item>The Razer may boldly graſe on a fools beard.</item>
                  <item>The lean man is Wolves meat.</item>
                  <item>The worſt ſtep is that over the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold.</item>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:115502:61"/>
                  <item>The beſt play on the board is not to play at all.</item>
                  <item>The Huntſmans breakfaſt the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers dinner.</item>
                  <item>The miſerable man makes a penny of a farthing, the liberall of a penny ſix pence.</item>
                  <item>There is no equity in keeping an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt promiſe.</item>
                  <item>The wiſeſt man ſaies leaſt.</item>
                  <item>The hole cals the thief.</item>
                  <item>The firſt love is the faſteſt.</item>
                  <item>The gentle Hawk half mans her ſelf.</item>
                  <item>The envious man ſhall never want wo.</item>
                  <item>The pompkin dies with the ſeed in its belly.</item>
                  <item>Thieves falling out true men come by their goods.</item>
                  <item>The Devilis not alwaies at one door.</item>
                  <item>Two hands in a diſh one in Purſe.</item>
                  <item>Thoſe that promiſe moſt perform leaſt.</item>
                  <item>There is no ſcourge of wit or learning that will laſh a wanton lover out of his luſt.</item>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:115502:62"/>
                  <item>The Mill cannot gride with the water that's paſt.</item>
                  <item>Time ſtayes not the fools leaſure.</item>
                  <item>The fools tears are not to be truſted.</item>
                  <item>The faireſt women in the Stews the handſomeſt mate at the Gallows.</item>
                  <item>The good uſage of a Maſter is a ſpur to an ingenious ſervant.</item>
                  <item>The ſluggard muſt be clad in rags.</item>
                  <item>The fault of the Horſe is put on the ſaddle.</item>
                  <item>The richer the Cobler the blacker his thumb.</item>
                  <item>The beſt remedy againſt an ill man is to keep at a diſtance.</item>
                  <item>The head of a fiſh is firſt tamed.</item>
                  <item>The begger may ſing before the thief.</item>
                  <item>True content is only in Heaven.</item>
                  <item>Though a lie be well dreſt it is ever over-ripe.</item>
                  <item>The eye of the Maſter makes the horſe fat.</item>
                  <item>True good is that which is eternal.</item>
                  <item>The beſt Cart may overthrow.</item>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:115502:62"/>
                  <item>There is no Knave like an Abbot that was a Monk.</item>
                  <item>The beſt is beſt cheap.</item>
                  <item>The Cat knows whoſe lips ſhe licks.</item>
                  <item>There are more threatned then ſtriken.</item>
                  <item>The belly thinks the throat is cut.</item>
                  <item>The higheſt tree hath the greateſt fall.</item>
                  <item>The ambitious man is never ſatisfied.</item>
                  <item>The blind eats many a fly.</item>
                  <item>The Fox when he cannot reach the Grapes ſaies they are not ripe.</item>
                  <item>The more the merrier the fewer the better cheer.</item>
                  <item>The faireſt Roſe in the end is wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
                  <item>Though the Maſtiff be gentle yet bite him not by the lip.</item>
                  <item>The Cat would eat fiſh but would not wet her feet.</item>
                  <item>Three helping one another bear the burden of ſix.</item>
                  <item>The more haſt the leſſe ſpeed.</item>
                  <item>The young Cock croweth as the old heareth.</item>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:115502:63"/>
                  <item>The Son full, and tattard the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter empty and fine.</item>
                  <item>The low ſtake ſtandeth long.</item>
                  <item>The longeſt day hath his end.</item>
                  <item>The faulty man ſtands on his Guard.</item>
                  <item>The Keys hang not all at one Girdle.</item>
                  <item>The ill that comes out of our mouth falls into our boſome.</item>
                  <item>That the eye ſeeth not the heart rueth not.</item>
                  <item>The lame gos as far as your ſtaggerer.</item>
                  <item>The tongue is not ſteel yet it cures.</item>
                  <item>Though the Fox run yet the Chickens have wings.</item>
                  <item>That penny is well ſpent that ſaveth a groat.</item>
                  <item>That is gold which is worth gold.</item>
                  <item>The firſt ſhour is that which wets moſt</item>
                  <item>The wolf muſt die in his own skin.</item>
                  <item>The rich knows not who is his friend.</item>
                  <item>They talk of Chriſtmas ſo long that it comes.</item>
                  <item>To a cloſe ſhorn ſheep God gives wind by meaſure.</item>
                  <item>That which ſuffereth is not little.</item>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:115502:63"/>
                  <item>There needs a long time to know the worlds Pulſe.</item>
                  <item>To him that hath loſt his taſt ſweet is ſoure.</item>
                  <item>They that hold the greateſt farmes pay the leaſt rent: applied to rich men that are unthankfull to God.</item>
                  <item>There is no wo to want.</item>
                  <item>Two heads are better then one.</item>
                  <item>Tales of <hi>Robbin Hood</hi> are good for fools.</item>
                  <item>The command of Cuſtom is great.</item>
                  <item>That one will not another will.</item>
                  <item>The leg doth what the knee would have it.</item>
                  <item>To deceive the deceiver is no deceit.</item>
                  <item>Tith and be rich.</item>
                  <item>The lame Poſt brings the true news.</item>
                  <item>The burnt Child dreads the fire.</item>
                  <item>Threatned folks live long.</item>
                  <item>Take heed is a good need.</item>
                  <item>Take time when time cometh left time ſtealeth away.</item>
                  <item>The eye is a ſhrew.</item>
                  <item>Thurſday come and the week gone.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:115502:64"/>
            </div>
            <div n="V" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>VIrtue never grows old.</item>
                  <item>Virtue and a Trade are the beſt portions for Children.</item>
                  <item>Under a threadbare cloak lies many times much learning.</item>
                  <item>Vallour that Parlies is near yeelding.</item>
                  <item>Unſound minds like unſound bodies if you feed you poyſon.</item>
                  <item>Unwonted Objects breed unwonted thoughts.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="VV" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>VVOrds ar womens deeds.</item>
                  <item>When the Fox preaches beware the Geeſe.</item>
                  <item>Winter thunder makes Summers wonder.</item>
                  <item>Who repents chaſtizeth himſelf.</item>
                  <item>Who takes bond for money truſts his Eſtate not his Perſon.</item>
                  <item>Wit is never good till bought.</item>
                  <item>Who hath no memory let him have legs.</item>
                  <item>What your glaſſe tells you will not
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:115502:64"/>be tould by counſell.</item>
                  <item>Where Coyn is not, commons muſt be ſcant.</item>
                  <item>When the Cat is away the mice play.</item>
                  <item>Wine and women have conſumed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Lordſhip.</item>
                  <item>Who that may not as they will muſt as they may.</item>
                  <item>Well bred ſpirits ſeldome degenerate.</item>
                  <item>Wares dear bought are ſeldom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn without loſſe.</item>
                  <item>While the diſcreet adviſe, the fool hath his buſineſſe.</item>
                  <item>Who goes willingly goes twice.</item>
                  <item>Win gold and wear gold.</item>
                  <item>When all ſins grow old covetouſneſſe grows young.</item>
                  <item>Who doth his own buſineſſe fouls not his hands.</item>
                  <item>Who wed ere he be wiſe ſhall dye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thrive.</item>
                  <item>Who drives another mans Trade make a ſop in a panier.</item>
                  <item>Weight juſtly and ſell dearly.</item>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:115502:65"/>
                  <item>Who ſo that knew what would be dear ſhould need be a Marchant but one year.</item>
                  <item>Were there not fools bad ware would not paſſe.</item>
                  <item>When there is a plague in Caſtile the infection is generall.</item>
                  <item>Where no fault is there needs no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</item>
                  <item>Who ſo blind as they that will not ſee?</item>
                  <item>Will you? is ſpoken to ſick Folkes.</item>
                  <item>We Batchellers ſhew our teeth, but you married-men laugh till your heart ake.</item>
                  <item>Who will borrow when he hath not let him borrow when he hath.</item>
                  <item>Who is ſo deaf as he that will not hear?</item>
                  <item>Women, Money, and Wine, have there good and there evil.</item>
                  <item>Who will do ill never wants occaſion.</item>
                  <item>Would you know what money is? go borrow ſome.</item>
                  <item>Who goes to bed Supperleſſe all
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:115502:65"/>night tumbles and toſſes.</item>
                  <item>Wealth is like Rhume it fals on the weakeſt part.</item>
                  <item>Water afar of quencheth not fire.</item>
                  <item>Wiſdome hath one foot on the land, another on the ſea.</item>
                  <item>Where many words are the truth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten goeth by.</item>
                  <item>Who can ſing a merrier Note then he that cannot change a Groat?</item>
                  <item>Wine in bottels doth not quench the thirſt.</item>
                  <item>We can have no more of a Cat then her skin.</item>
                  <item>Whether ſhall the Ox go where he ſhall not labour?</item>
                  <item>Who invites bears the danger.</item>
                  <item>Who gives to all denyes all.</item>
                  <item>What's a workman without tools?</item>
                  <item>Whoſe houſe is of glaſſe muſt not throw ſtones at another.</item>
                  <item>When the belly is full the bones would be at reſt.</item>
                  <item>Who hath no more bread then need muſt not keep a dog.</item>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:115502:66"/>
                  <item>Who beſtows a bow on thee wiſhes thee not dead.</item>
                  <item>When the Iron is hot ſtrike.</item>
                  <item>Who tels his ſecrets makes himſelf a ſlave.</item>
                  <item>Wine is a turncoat, firſt a friend then an enemy.</item>
                  <item>Who lets his wife go to every Feaſt, and his horſe to every water, ſhall neither have good wife, nor a good horſe.</item>
                  <item>Willows are weak yet they bind o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others.</item>
                  <item>Women laught when they can weep when they will.</item>
                  <item>Who ſo bold as blind bayard.</item>
                  <item>What's a fool without a bable?</item>
                  <item>Well may he ſmell fire whoſe gown burns.</item>
                  <item>Whores affect your purſe not you.</item>
                  <item>Who more buſie then he that hath leaſt to do.</item>
                  <item>Wiſdome is better then riches.</item>
                  <item>When Prayers are done my Lady is ready.</item>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:115502:66"/>
                  <item>We muſt not judge of men by their birth but by their breeding.</item>
                  <item>What the heart thinketh the tongue ſpeaketh.</item>
                  <item>Who means to have the egge muſt endure the cackling of the Hen.</item>
                  <item>What ſome win in the hundred they looſe in the ſhire.</item>
                  <item>When a friend askes there's no to morrow.</item>
                  <item>Who labours is tempted by one De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, but who ſtands idle by a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</item>
                  <item>When <hi>Italy</hi> ſhall be without poyſon, <hi>France</hi> without treaſon, <hi>England</hi> without war, the world ſhall be without earth.</item>
                  <item>Who means to be lean muſt keep his eyes open and his mouth ſhut.</item>
                  <item>When the sky falls we ſhall have Larks.</item>
                  <item>Who hath no mind to his buſineſſe valleys ſeem mountains.</item>
                  <item>What needs words where there are works?</item>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115502:67"/>
                  <item>When the Sun ſhines make Hay.</item>
                  <item>Who buyes hath need of a hundred eyes, who ſells hath enough of one.</item>
                  <item>We learn for to underſtand, not for to diſpute.</item>
                  <item>Where nothing is a little doth eaſe.</item>
                  <item>When a Lackey comes to hels door the devil locks the gate.</item>
                  <item>Women love to be ey'd and to be lookt upon.</item>
                  <item>Who makes a Cart knows alſo how to take it in pieces.</item>
                  <item>Water, fire, and Souldiers, quickly make room.</item>
                  <item>Women are young mens Miſtreſſes, middle-ag'd mens Companions, and old mens Nurſes.</item>
                  <item>When the danger is paſt the fact is forgotten.</item>
                  <item>What need a contentious man marry?</item>
                  <item>When a dog is drowned every one offers him help.</item>
                  <item>Where ſhall a man have a worſe friend then he brings from home?</item>
                  <item>Who removes ſtones bruiſe their fingers.</item>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:115502:67"/>
                  <item>Without buſineſſe debauchery.</item>
                  <item>Where nothing is the King muſt loſe his right.</item>
                  <item>Who hath a wolf for his mate needs a dog for his man.</item>
                  <item>Who readeth to others readeth alſo to himſelf.</item>
                  <item>Whatſoever was the Father of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe an ill dyet was the mother.</item>
                  <item>We know not who lives or dies.</item>
                  <item>Words are not Links.</item>
                  <item>Whores and dogs fawn upon a man no longer then they are fed.</item>
                  <item>VVere there no hearers there would be no backbyters.</item>
                  <item>VVere there no receivers there would be no thieves.</item>
                  <item>VVhether you boyl Snow or pound it you can have but water of it.</item>
                  <item>VVine makes all ſorts of creatures at Table.</item>
                  <item>VVho covets all dies a mad man.</item>
                  <item>VVhile the graſſe grows the ſteed ſtarves.</item>
                  <item>VVho is worſe ſhod then the Shooe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers wife.</item>
                  <pb n="224" facs="tcp:115502:68"/>
                  <item>VVhen age is jocond it makes ſport for death.</item>
                  <item>VVar is deaths Feaſt.</item>
                  <item>VVhere there is no honour there is no grief.</item>
                  <item>VVine that coſt nothing is digeſted before it be drank.</item>
                  <item>VVhere the drink goes in the wit goes out.</item>
                  <item>VVhere you will is ready your feet is light.</item>
                  <item>VVithout hope the heart would break.</item>
                  <item>VVhen God will no wind but brings rain.</item>
                  <item>VVood half burnt is eaſily kindled.</item>
                  <item>VVeight and meaſure take away ſtrife.</item>
                  <item>VVho hunts two Hares loſeth the one and deſerts the other.</item>
                  <item>VVhen the Horſe is ſtollen ſhut the Stable door.</item>
                  <item>VVhen my houſe burnes it's not good playing at Cheſſe.</item>
                  <item>VVho lacketh a ſtock his gain is not worth a chip.</item>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:115502:68"/>
                  <item>VVar makes thieves and Peace hangs them.</item>
                  <item>VVho haſtens a glutton choaks him.</item>
                  <item>VVho receives forgets not.</item>
                  <item>VVho praiſeth St. <hi>Peter</hi> doth not blame St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VVho ſo fears a dog enſures himſelf from being bitten.</item>
                  <item>VVho payes the Phyſician does the cure.</item>
                  <item>VVhen one is on horsback he knows all things.</item>
                  <item>VViſh not for a Horſe that is bridled at the tayl.</item>
                  <item>VVhen you enter into a houſe leave the anger at door.</item>
                  <item>VVhom weale pricks ſorrow comes after and licks.</item>
                  <item>VVar and Phyſick are governed by the eye.</item>
                  <item>VVine ever payes for for his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                  <item>VVith Cuſtomes we live well but Laws undoe us.</item>
                  <item>VVhen all men have what belongs to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:115502:69"/>them it cannot be much.</item>
                  <item>VVho hath eaten the Candles void the weekes.</item>
                  <item>VVe leave more to do when we die then we have done.</item>
                  <item>VVho gives well ſells dear.</item>
                  <item>VVho attempts not errs not.</item>
                  <item>VVhen a man ſleeps his head is in his ſtomack.</item>
                  <item>VVho hath money and Capers is well furniſht for Lent.</item>
                  <item>VVhen God is made the Maſter of a Family he diſorders the diſorderly.</item>
                  <item>VVhere gold ſpeaks every tongue is ſilent.</item>
                  <item>VVords and feathers the wind car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries away.</item>
                  <item>VVho embraces all nothing graſpes.</item>
                  <item>VVe do it ſoon enough if that we do be well.</item>
                  <item>VVo be to him that reads but one Book.</item>
                  <item>VVho gives good words feeds with an empty ſpoon.</item>
                  <item>VVho lives in hopes dies a Fool.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:115502:69"/>
            </div>
            <div n="Y" type="proverbs">
               <list>
                  <item>YOu muſt loſe a fly to catch a gnat.</item>
                  <item>You ſhall know what a man is worth when he is dead.</item>
                  <item>You come with your five egges and four of them addled.</item>
                  <item>You may know what a man is by his company.</item>
                  <item>You had as live go to Mill as to maſſe.</item>
                  <item>Years know more then Books.</item>
                  <item>Your thoughts cloſe and your counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance loſe.</item>
                  <item>Young men may die but old men muſt die.</item>
                  <item>You need not ſow weeds.</item>
                  <item>You cannot ſee wood for trees.</item>
                  <item>You cannot hide an ell in a ſack.</item>
                  <item>You are as ſeaſonable as ſnow in winter.</item>
                  <item>You cannot know Wine by the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</item>
                  <item>You cannot flea a ſtone.</item>
                  <item>You muſt loſe a fly to catch a Trout.</item>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:115502:70"/>
                  <item>Young Saint old Devil.</item>
                  <item>You cannot make a fire ſo low but it will go out.</item>
                  <item>Ynough is as good as a Feaſt.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="sentences">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:115502:70"/>
               <head>Wiſe SPEECHES, <hi>AND</hi> Golden SENTENCES.</head>
               <p n="1">1. GIve me the heart of a man, and out of that all other deeds ſhall be acceptable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When thou haſt taken unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, reſtore it ſpeedily; for the ſin in taking, is repeated every minute thou keepeſt it: if thou canſt, reſtore it in kind, if not, in value; if it may be, reſtore it to the party, if not, to God: The poor is Gods receiver.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was ſaid of <hi>Nero,</hi> that though he could tune his Harp well, yet in his Government he did alwaies wind up the ſtrings to high, or let them down to low.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:115502:71"/>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Severus</hi> the Emperour being but meanly born, and having raiſed himſelf to that high honour, was wont to ſay, <hi>I have been all, and am never the better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Cato</hi> had this ſaying, <hi>That the beſt way to keep good acts in memory, was to refreſh them with new.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. A private Souldier (ſeeing <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> vainly pufft up with a great Victory over the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi>) took courage and told him, <hi>That if he meaſured his own ſhadow, be ſhould find it no longer then it was before his victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Doſt thou want things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, grumble not? perchance it was a neceſſary thus thou ſhouldſt want; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour lawfully to ſupply it, if God bleſs not thy endeavour, bleſs him, that knoweth what is fitteſt for thee; thou art Gods Patient, preſcribe not thy Phyſician.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It's no ſhame to be poor, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided thou keep thy ſelf honeſt in thy poverty.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:115502:71"/>
               <p n="9">9. It's the greateſt folly in youth, either not to endeavour good advice, or not to believe it till their perill comes upon them, and makes them ſee it to their ſhtme.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Rich <hi>Croeſus</hi> ſhewing <hi>Solon</hi> the Philoſopher a great heap of gold that he had gathered together, askt him what he thought of it, who confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently replied, <hi>If another come that hath better iron then you, he will be Maſter of all this gold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. He that profeſſeth himſelf thy open enemy, arm thee againſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil he means thee; but he that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles himſelf thy ſecret friend, ſtrikes beyond caution, and wounds above cure: From the firſt thou maiſt deliver thy ſelf, from the laſt good Lord deliver thee.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Errours by miſtakes ſhould not be too vigourouſly cenſured, but errours that be wilfull ſhould not be ſpared.</p>
               <p n="13">13. It was a wiſe ſaying of a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:115502:72"/>Senatour of <hi>Rome</hi> (during the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Galba</hi> who being aged, the people took liberty and had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt brought all into confuſion) <hi>That it were better to live where nothing is lawfull, then where all things are lawfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. It's a certain Rule in all dark Propheſies, That they are never clearly underſtood, till they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Correction without Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is but meer tyranny.</p>
               <p n="16">16. All qualities, without directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of virtue profit not but overthrow their poſſeſſor.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Gold is tryed with the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, but men by gold.</p>
               <p n="18">18. As the Servants of God are known by humility and charity, ſo the ſervants of the Devil are known by pride and cruelty.</p>
               <p n="19">19. No man gains by war, but he that hath not wherewith to live in Peace.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:115502:72"/>
               <p n="20">20. Pray often becauſe thou ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt alwaies, repent quickly leſt thou die ſuddainly.</p>
               <p n="21">21. He is ſaid truly to ſerve his Countrey, whoſe body executeth what is wiſdom plotteth.</p>
               <p n="22">22. The honour of a King ſtands in the multitude of the people, but his ſafety in the love of his Subjects.</p>
               <p n="23">23. Be alwaies leſſe willing to ſpeak then to hear; when thou heareſt thou receiveſt, when thou ſpeakeſt thou giveſt; it is more glorious to give, more profitable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Prayer is one of the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt actions we do, for we ſpeak with God as it were, reaſoning with him; it brings down God from Heaven, and makes him grant our will, and dwell with us and we with him eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>Syward</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> lying on his ſick-bed, and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death approaching ſuddainly
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:115502:73"/>ſtarted out of his bed and put on his Armour, ſaying, <hi>It became not a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant man to die lying like a beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. If any ſpeak ill of thee, flee home to thy own conſcience and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine thy heart; if thou be guilty it's a juſt correction, if not guilty, it's a fair Inſtruction; make uſe of both, ſo ſhalt thou diſtill honey out of gall, and of an open enemy cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a ſecret friend.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Religious Almſ-deeds makes God become our debtour.</p>
               <p n="28">28. He is not worthy to command others, that cannot bridle his own af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and unreſonable appetite.</p>
               <p n="29">29. Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> in his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, was wont to comfort himſelf with this, ſaying, <hi>That the world was but a wide Priſon, and every day one or other was call'd out to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30. VVe complain of the times, and juſtly, for never more wicked; but let us take heed that we be not a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:115502:73"/>part of the miſery of the times, and they made worſe by our ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="31">31. Time the Mother, will bring forth Virtue the Daughter in due ſeaſon.</p>
               <p n="32">32. King <hi>Charles</hi> of ever bleſſed memory uſed this Speech to his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Parliament, <hi>That it is more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable for a King to be invaded, and almoſt deſtroyed by a forraign enemy, then to be deſpiſed at home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="33">33. Beware of drunkeneſſe, leſt all good men beware of thee: where drunkeneſſe reigns, there reaſon is an exile, Virtue a ſtranger, God an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, blaſphemy is wit, oathes are rhetorick, and ſecrets are proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Noah</hi> diſcovered that in one hour drunk, which ſober he kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſix hundred years.</p>
               <p n="34">34. <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Emperour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving laid a double Tax upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, one of his under Officers told him, <hi>If he would have the people pay two Taxes in one year, be ſhould give
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:115502:74"/>them two ſeed-times and two Harveſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="35">35. My Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That Laws were like cobwebs, where the ſmall flyes are caught, and the great flyes break through.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="36">36. If thou deſireſt reſt to thy ſoul, be juſt: for he that doth no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury fears not to ſuffer injury: The unjuſt mind is alwaies in labour, it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther practiſes the evil it hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, or projects to avoid the evil, it hath deſerved.</p>
               <p n="37">37. Falſe Miracles and lying News, are the food of ſuperſtition, which by credulity deludes ignorant people.</p>
               <p n="38">38. <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour was wont to ſay, <hi>That an unlearned King was a crowned aſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="39">39. A rich Merchant uſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to drink out of a wodden diſh, and being reproved for it by a friend, anſwered, <hi>I had rather drink out of Wood, and make golden payments, then drink out of gold, and make wooden payments.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:115502:74"/>
               <p n="40">40. In all thy actions, think God ſees thee, and in all his actions, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſee him; that will make thee fear him, this will move thee to love him.</p>
               <p n="41">41. Continual experience ſhews, That idleneſſe is the greateſt ſpur to lechery.</p>
               <p n="42">42. The Birds of the ayre die to ſuſtain thee, the beaſts of the field die to nouriſh thee, the fiſhes of the Sea die to feed thee: Our ſtomacks are their common Sepulchre. Good God, with how many deaths are our poor lives patcht up of? How full of death is the miſerable life of mortal man?</p>
               <p n="43">43. Suggeſtions are needleſs from abroad, when the miſchief is felt at home.</p>
               <p n="44">44. It is a hard thing to be rich and honoured in this world, and not ſtruk with the dart of pride and vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p n="45">45. A heart not exerciſed in ſome honeſt calling, works trouble out of it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:115502:75"/>
               <p n="46">46. The Devil never aſſaults a man, except he find him either void of knowledge, or the fear of God.</p>
               <p n="47">47. Rebuke thy Servants fault in private, publique Reproofs hardens his ſhame: if he be paſt a youth, ſtrike him not; he is not fit for thy Service, that after wiſe reproofs will either deſerve thy ſtrokes, or digeſt them.</p>
               <p n="48">48. God hath left three Books in the world, in each of which he may eaſily be found; The Book of the Creatures, the Book of Conſcience, and his written Word. The firſt ſhews his Omnipotency, the ſecond his Juſtice, the third his Mercy and Goodneſſe.</p>
               <p n="49">49. Nothing inſlaveth a gratefull Nature like a free benefit; he that conferrs it on me, ſteals me from my ſelf, and in one and the ſame art, makes me a vaſſell, and himſelf my King.</p>
               <p n="50">50. A prating Barber coming to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:115502:75"/>trim King <hi>Archelaus,</hi> askt him, Sir, How will you pleaſe to have me cut your hair? The King ſilently anſwered; <hi>Though a man hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do but to hear and anſwer, yet a limitleſs tongue is a ſtrange unbitted beaſt to worry one with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="51">51. They that ſpeak much, ſeldom ſpeak well: for they that know how to ſpeak right, know not how to dwell in diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="52">52. He that hath a Wife and Children, hath given Hoſtages to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; for they are Impediments to great enterpriſes.</p>
               <p n="53">53. Men in great places are thrice Servants; Servants of the Soveraign or State, Servants of Fame, or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Buſineſſe: So that they may be truly ſaid, to have no free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom neither in their Perſons nor in their Actions.</p>
               <p n="54">54. Riches may truly be cal'd the baggage of Virtue, for of great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches there is no reall uſe, except it be
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:115502:76"/>in diſtribution, thereſt is but conceited.</p>
               <p n="55">55. Kings and Emperours are in a miſerable condition, for they have few things to deſire, and many things to fear.</p>
               <p n="56">56. <hi>Plato</hi> obſerved, <hi>That all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was but remembrance.</hi> And <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>That all novelty is but Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion.</hi> There is nothing in this world that may be ſaid to be perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, but the two great winding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheets that bury all things in oblivion, Deluges and Earthquakes.</p>
               <p n="57">57. Muſick is more for pleaſure then profit to man-kind, which cauſed <hi>Diogenes</hi> to ſay to one that brag'd in his skill, <hi>That wiſdome govern'd Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but with Songs and Muſick he could not expect to order a Houſe well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="58">58. After a long ſenſe of Peace War enters the ſtage, and indeed it is the worlds Phyſick, it's both a a Purge and a Blood-letting: Peace, Fullneſs, Pride, and War, are the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:115502:76"/>four fellies that being let into one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, makes the wheel that the times turn on.</p>
               <p n="59">59. One asking <hi>Diogenes</hi> what was the ſaddeſt creature in the world, he anſwered, <hi>An old man in poverty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="60">60. It argues a baſe diſpoſition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for favour or frowns, to deſert a good cauſe in evil times.</p>
               <p n="61">61. Wouldſt thou multiply thy Riches, diminiſh them wiſely, or wouldſt thou make thy eſtate entire, divide it charitably: Seeds that are ſcattered, encreaſe, but hoarded up, they periſh.</p>
               <p n="62">62. No man ſhall do ill that thinks ere he undertakes what the end will be, not what his paſſion will have it to be.</p>
               <p n="63">63. In an age of plottings (as theſe are in which we live) the deepeſt plot is to be ſaved, and the beſt poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is to get aſſurance of Heaven.</p>
               <p n="64">64. Revenge is ſweet to mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it may fitly be compared to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:115502:77"/>the arrow that flyes in the dark. <hi>Ceſmus</hi> Duke of <hi>Florence</hi> had a deſperate ſaying againſt perfidious Friends, <hi>(We read that we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to forgive our enemies, but we never read that we are commanded to forgive our Friends.) That man which ſtudies Revenge, keeps his own wounds green, which otherwiſe would heal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="65">65. He was a wiſe man, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing askt what was the beſt time to marry in, made this anſwer; <hi>For a young man not yet, for an elder man not at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="66">66. <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> a great enemy to the Jeſuites, who when he had taken away their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, cauſed the old Jeſuites to be hang'd, and ſent the young to the Mines, ſaying, <hi>That ſince they wrought ſo hard above ground he would try how they could work under ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="67">67. To beſtow benefits on the bad, makes them worſe, and villi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth the reward of the virtuous.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:115502:77"/>
               <p n="68">68. This wiſe ſaying of of Sir <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Wotton, That the itch of Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will at laſt prove the ſcab of the Church,</hi> will eternize his Name more then all the monuments, that Art can poſſibly deviſe.</p>
               <p n="69">69. Be not unſtable in thy Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, nor various in thy Actions, nor inconſtant in thy Affections; ſo deliberate, that thou maiſt reſolve, ſo reſolve, that thou maiſt perform: Mutability is the badge of Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p n="70">70. As the natural body is delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in change, ſo alſo is the politique body greedy of alterations.</p>
               <p n="71">71. He ſaid truly, That buying of Church Lands, would be a mouth to eat up the reſt of the Purchaſers E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
               <p n="72">72. There is no truſt in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, (as we have lately ſeen by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience,) one day they adore, the next rebell; to day cry <hi>Hail, Hail;</hi> to morrow <hi>Crucify.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:115502:78"/>
               <p n="73">73. There is nothing the nature of man can leſs brook then Reproach, for there is no man ſo mean but thinks himſelf worthy of ſome regard.</p>
               <p n="74">74. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid, That perfect glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiſts in three things; If the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude lov'd a man, if they will truſt him, if they hold him worthy of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, praiſe, and honour.</p>
               <p n="75">75. The Stoicks affirm'd, That to live agreeable to nature, was to live virtuouſly and valiantly.</p>
               <p n="76">76. The Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> Treaſurer to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> was wont to ſay, That he <hi>overcame envy and ill will, more by patience then pertinacy.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Camden</hi> ſaid of him, That he was amongſt thoſe few <hi>that lived and died with glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="77">77. At the Battell of <hi>Newport,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> having the Spaniſh Army before him, and the Sea behind him, ſpake thus to his Souldiers; <hi>If you will live, you muſt either eat up theſe Spaniards, or drink up this Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:115502:78"/>
               <p n="78">78. <hi>Alexander</hi> having a Souldier of his Name under him, that was a coward, bid him <hi>either leave off his Name, or ceaſe being a Souldier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="79">79. A confident woman came cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring to <hi>Gratian</hi> the Emperour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Husband, to whom the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour mildly anſwered, <hi>What is that to me?</hi> ſhe preſently told him, That he had ſpoken Treaſon againſt him: He again replied, <hi>What is that to thee?</hi> Which cauſed the woman to go away aſhamed.</p>
               <p n="80">80. It was the uſual ſaying of a French Poet, <hi>That he was not happy that had the things that he deſired, but he which did not deſire the things he had not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="81">81. A Baſhaw of <hi>Turky,</hi> perſwading the Emperour not to make war upon the <hi>Germanes</hi> by reaſon of their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, who anſwered; <hi>That his fingers would ſooner be all of a length, then their Princes be all of one mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="82">82. <hi>Cato</hi> ſpeaking of the authority
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:115502:79"/>that the Women of <hi>Rome</hi> had over their Husbands, ſaid, <hi>Other men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand their Wives; we command men, and our Wives command us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="83">83. Do well while thou maiſt, leſt thou do evil when thou wouldſt not: He that takes not advantage of a good power, ſhall loſe the benefit of a good will.</p>
               <p n="84">84. Mans happineſſe reſts in the managing of his own time; ſo that every man may be bleſt, and rich in perfection, if his own dſſioluteneſſe and unthriftineſſe incurres not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p n="85">85. <hi>Cato</hi> was wont to ſay, that in all his life time, it repented him of three things: 1. That ever he had told a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to a woman. 2. That he went by water when he might have gone by Land. 3. That he had been idle a whole day and done nothing.</p>
               <p n="86">86. In all Nations two things are Cauſes of a common <hi>proſperity;</hi> Good <hi>Government,</hi> and Good <hi>Obedience:</hi>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:115502:79"/>A good <hi>Magistrate</hi> over a perverſe <hi>people, is a ſound head on a ſurfeited body;</hi> a good <hi>Commonalty</hi> and a bad <hi>Ruler,</hi> is a <hi>ſound body with a head-ach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="87">87. The wiſdome of <hi>Simonides</hi> was very commendable, who being askt by <hi>Hiero</hi> what he thought of God, deſired a ſeven nights ſpace to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it; at the ſeven nights end, he askt a fortnights; at the fortnights end, a moneth; at which <hi>Hiero</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, <hi>Simonides</hi> anſwered, <hi>That the longer he thought of it, the more difficult he found it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="88">88. The way whereby Faith qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eteth the ſoul, is by raiſing it above all diſcontentments and ſtormes here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and pitching it on God.</p>
               <p n="89">89. <hi>Alexander</hi> was not commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for conquering the world, but for doing it before he was thirty years of age.</p>
               <p n="90">90. A full ſwinge in pleaſure, is the way to make men ſenſleſſe; a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent perſwaſion of unavoidably miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:115502:80"/>is a ready path to deſpair.</p>
               <p n="91">91. Three things neceſſary for a Chriſtian to know; <hi>His own miſery, Gods love, his own thankfull obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="92">92. It was good counſell the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher gave the young men of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; That they ſhould often view themſelves in a glaſs; if they were fair and well featur'd, that they ſhould do thoſe things that were beſeeming their amiable ſhape; but if foul and ill-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd, that then they ſhould labour to ſalve the bodies blemiſhes by the beauties of a mind accountred with the ornaments of virtue and good literature:</hi> All which is fitly applicable to a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="93">93. It was King <hi>James</hi> his adviſe, <hi>That we ſhould not be like the Puritan in our Prayers, who ſpeak to God as to there fellows, and ſit at Chriſts Table as with their companions, but to joyn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence with the ſweet confidence we have in Gods love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="74">74. It is better to follow the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of them whom we love not,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:115502:80"/>then in defects, reſemble them whom we love.</p>
               <p n="95">95. In chooſing a friend, beſure to avoid two ſorts of men: 1. Drunkard: 2. A paſſionate man. For, the firſt, he ſpeaks what he knows not, nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter can he remember what that was he ſpake; for the other, in his fit he is perfectly mad, and ſpeaks not a word by reaſon, but by bruitiſh paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: for anger is the feaver of the ſoul.</p>
               <p n="96">96. Peace from the mouth of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant is oftner promiſed then perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p n="97">97. Love breaks the brain, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bruiſeth the brow; it conſumeth the heart, but never toucheth the skin, and makes a deep ſcar be ſeen, before any wound be felt.</p>
               <p n="98">98. Envy never caſts her eye low, nor ambition never points but alwaies upward.</p>
               <p n="99">99. That man that hath married a virtuous Wife, may truly be ſaid to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:115502:81"/>be happy; for being on earth, he hath attain'd Heaven; being in want, hath attain'd wealth; being in wo, hath attain'd comfort.</p>
               <p n="100">100. The holieſt man in ſhew, proves commonly the holloweſt man in heart.</p>
               <p n="101">101. It is better to have an open enemy then a diſſembling Friend.</p>
               <p n="102">102. The heart of a fool is in his mouth, but the mouth of a wiſe man is in his heart.</p>
               <p n="103">103. Miſtruſt no man without cauſe, neither be thou credulous with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proof.</p>
               <p n="104">104. Words wittily ſpoken awake and revive the judgment, but exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples perſwade the heart.</p>
               <p n="105">105. Wiſdom was begot by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nouriſht by experience, and brought forth by learning.</p>
               <p n="106">106. Of all the Treaſures in a Common-wealth, the innocent man is moſt to be eſteemed.</p>
               <p n="107">107. Happy is that Countrey
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:115502:81"/>whoſe <hi>Captaines</hi> are <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> are <hi>Captaines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="108">108. Honour is brittle, and Riches are bloſſoms, which every froſt of fortune cauſeth to wither.</p>
               <p n="109">109. He that through cuſtom makes little account of his promiſe, may ſwear often, but ſhall ſeldom be believed.</p>
               <p n="110">110. A man having honour and wanting wiſdom, is like a fair tree without fruit.</p>
               <p n="111">111. The evenings hope may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the mornings miſery.</p>
               <p n="112">112. A poor man being in charity is rich, but a rich man without cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is poor.</p>
               <p n="113">113. Time and Patience teach all men to be content.</p>
               <p n="114">114. A fooliſh man beginneth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, and endeth nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:82"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:82"/>
            <head>Curteous Reader, Theſe Books follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are Printed for <hi>Simon Miller,</hi> and Sold by him at the Starre in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Small Folio.</head>
               <item>DOctor <hi>Lightfoot</hi> his Harmony on the New Teſtament, which will ſhortly be re-print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with large Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</item>
               <item>The Civil Warres of <hi>Spain</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Germany,</hi> and King of that Nation, wherein our late unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py differences are paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leled in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larss.</item>
               <item>A general Hiſtory of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the year 767. to the death of King <hi>James,</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the principal Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and State, with Political Obſervations, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the ſame: by <hi>David Hume</hi> of <hi>Godſcroft.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of this Iron Age.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul Baine</hi> on the <hi>Epheſians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Queen of <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> a Play: In <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In Quarto large.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jo. Barklay</hi> his <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genis,</hi> Tranſlated by Sir <hi>Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Griſe</hi> Knight, by his Late Majeſties ſpecial Command.</item>
               <item>An Eperimental Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Surgery, by <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix Wortz.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:83"/>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto Small.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith, or the good Old Religion, proving the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be the only true Faith of Gods Elect: By <hi>John Nicholſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>The Anatomy of Mortality: By <hi>George Strood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three Treatiſes: 1. The Converſion of <hi>Nineveh</hi> touching Frayer and Faſting. 2. Gods Trumpet ſounding to Repentance. 3. Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign preſervatives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſtruſtfull Thoughts and Cares: By <hi>Will. Atterſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aynſworth</hi> on the <hi>Canticles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paul Baine,</hi> his <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſans</hi> Trial.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gralle</hi> againſt <hi>Appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of Civil policy, being a clear Deciſion of 43 Queries, concerning prerogative, right and priviledge, in reference to the ſupream Prince and people: By <hi>Samuel Rutherford</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Divinity of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Andrews</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Politick and Military Obſervations of Civil and Military Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, containing the Birth, Encreaſe, Decay of Monarchies, the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of Princes and Magiſtrates.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Pinchin</hi> his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious price of mans Redemption, cleared.</item>
               <item>Aſtrology Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſhewing what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and influence the Starres and Planets have over men, and how the ſame may be diverted and avoided.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wells</hi> his Souls Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs.</item>
               <item>Chriſt tempted, the Devils Conquered; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a plain Expoſition on the fourth Chapter of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſpel: By <hi>John Gumbledon</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>The Saints Society.</item>
               <item>Dr <hi>Stoughtons</hi> thirteen
<pb facs="tcp:115502:83"/>choice Sermons, with his Body of Divinity.</item>
               <item>The Reaſons of the diſſenting Brethren con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Presbyterian Government, together with the anſwer of the Aſſembly of Divines.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gamdens</hi> Remains.</item>
               <item>The Harmonious Conſent and Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, of all the Proteſtant Reformed Churches in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</item>
               <item>The diſcription of the Univerſall Quadrant, by which is perform'd with great Expedition, the whole Doctrine of Triangles, both plain and Sphericall: Alſo the Reſolution of ſuch Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſitions as are moſt uſefull in <hi>Aſtronomy, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, and Dialling:</hi> By which is performed the proportioning of Lines for meaſuring of all manner of Land, Board, Glaſs, Timber, Stone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Tho. Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup</hi> Mathemat.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Large Octavo.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Florus Anglicus,</hi> with the Lively Effigies of all the Kings and Queens ſince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, cut in Braſs.</item>
               <item>The Reconciler of the Bible, wherein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two thouſand ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Contradictions are fully and plainly Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled.</item>
               <item>Evidences for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, containing infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Signs and real De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Salvation: publiſhed by <hi>Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manbury, Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Life and Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> from his Birth to his Death, By <hi>Lambert Wood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Night-Search, the ſecond part: By <hi>H. Mill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A view of the Jewiſh Religion, with their Rites, Cuſtomes and Ceremonies.</item>
               <item>Uſefull Inſtructions for theſe Evil times;
<pb facs="tcp:115502:84"/>held forth in 22 Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, by <hi>Nicholas Lockyer,</hi> Provoſt of <hi>Eaton</hi> Colledge</item>
               <item>The Nullity of Church-Cenſures, or Excommunication, not of Divine Inſtitution, but a meer humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention: Written by the famous <hi>Tho. Eraſtes,</hi> and never before Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Small Octavo.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ed Waterhouſe</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> His Diſcourſe of Piety and Charity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Panacea,</hi> or the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Medicine; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Diſcourſe of the Admirable Nature and Virtues of Tobacco: By Dr. <hi>Everard</hi> and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</item>
               <item>A view and Defence of the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> very uſefull in theſe times.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Pet. du Moulin,</hi> his Antidote againſt Popery; publiſhed on purpoſe to prevent the Deluſions of the Prieſts and Jeſuites who are now very buſie amongſt us</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Herberts</hi> Devotions, or a Companion for a Chriſtian, containing Meditations and prayers uſefull upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id de Pento,</hi> in Engliſh.</item>
               <item>The Loves of <hi>Cli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io</hi> and <hi>Lezio</hi> a Romance. Mr. <hi>Know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> his Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Hebrew Tongue.</item>
               <item>A Book of Scheams or Figures of Heaven, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſet for every four Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of times, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſefull for all Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Florus Anglicus,</hi> or an exact Hiſtory of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> from the Reig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>William</hi> to the death of the Late King.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lingua,</hi> or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of the Tongue, and five Senſes for Speri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority: a ſerious Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</item>
               <item>The Spirits Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; being a clear
<pb facs="tcp:115502:84"/>diſcovery how a man may certainly know whether he be truly taught by the Spirit of God, or not.</item>
               <item>The poor mans Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician and Chyrurgion.</item>
               <item>Phyſicall Rarities, containing the moſt choice Receipts in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and Chyrurgery, for the cure of all Diſeaſes Incident to mans body: By <hi>R W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lliams.</hi> To which is added the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Mathematicks: By <hi>Hermes, Triſ. Magiſtus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Idol of Clowns, or the Relation of <hi>Wat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iler</hi>'s Rebellion.</item>
               <item>The Chriſtian Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, in 3 parts.</item>
               <item>The Golden Fleece, or a Diſcourſe of the cloathing of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Sibbs</hi> his Divine Meditations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vigerius Preceptes</hi> of <hi>Idiotiſmes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Grotij Poemata.</item>
               <item>Three Books of Mr. <hi>Mathews</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Swanſey</hi> in <hi>Southwales.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 The Meſſiah Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the mouthes of Babes in <hi>America;</hi> or <hi>Gaius</hi> and <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a helpfull Father and his hopefull Son diſcourſing of the three moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable points: 1. The great want of Chriſt 2. The great worth. that is in Chriſt. 3. The good way that is chalkt our by Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>2. The New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall Church prov'd to be the old Chriſtian Church, by Scripture, Reaſon, and Hiſtory.</item>
                     <item>3. The Rending Church-member R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly cal'd back to Chriſt and his Church.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>A Phyſical Dictionary.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Duodecim.</head>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Smith</hi>'s pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of phyſick.</item>
               <item>The G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ammar War.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poſſellius Apothegmes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faſcicul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> Florum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Craſhaw</hi>'s Viſions.</item>
               <item>The Juniper Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Helvicus Colloquies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Chriſtian Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier,
<pb facs="tcp:115502:85"/>his Combate with the three arch-enemies of man-kind, the world, the fleſh, and the devil.</item>
               <item>Henſius de Crepundiis.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> or the Government of the Emperour of <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and faſhions of the people of that Countrey.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drexeliu</hi>'s School of Patience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drexelius</hi> his right Intention of every ones Action.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Vigimi Quat.</head>
               <item>The New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               <item>The third part of the Bible.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi>'s Med. and Prayers fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every day of the Week.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Playes.</head>
               <item>The Ball.</item>
               <item>Chawbut.</item>
               <item>Conſpiracy.</item>
               <item>Obſtinate Lady.</item>
               <item>The <hi>London</hi> Chanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clers; a Comedy full of various and delightfull Mirth, never before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:85"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115502:86"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
